中文字幕
All right.
This CS50 and this is lecture 7 wherein we pick up
中文字幕
where we left off last time in talking more about Python,
but this time using Python for even more powerful purposes,
中文字幕
an alliteration I didn't intend until I just said it there.
But the goal here with Python now is to actually use
中文字幕
this language to generate another language, in particular HTML.
And what we'll do is start to provide all the more of a mental model
中文字幕
for what you would call separation of concerns, whereby
when you design more complicated web based, or rather when you design
中文字幕
more complicated software, you tend to try to adopt certain design patterns so
that you're not just writing everything in one big file that
中文字幕
gets a little confusing, unwieldy to maintain and to add to over time.
But you start to separate your concerns, and your functionality,
中文字幕
and your features, and your collaborators' work
into different files and different methodologies.
中文字幕
So we'll try to give you some of these industry standard approaches today
and why they actually solved problems.
中文字幕
But, of course, how did we get here?
A few weeks ago, we talked about this thing,
中文字幕
this virtual envelope that just represents
packets of information, zeros and ones, going across the internet from point A
中文字幕
to point B. And among the messages in these envelopes
might be for web requests.
中文字幕
And we talked about HTTP, a protocol, hypertext transfer protocol,
that just sends message like this inside of the envelope.
中文字幕
And this is requesting, of course, the default page
of a website as implied by the slash.
中文字幕
And in many cases, but not always, this implies
a default file name of index.html.
中文字幕
But that's a human convention, not a requirement.
Hopefully, the server responds with a numeric code equal to what integer?
中文字幕
200, hopefully, a number that we never actually
really see unless you get more comfortable
中文字幕
and start poking around Chrome's inspector
and you look at your network traffic.
中文字幕
Right.
So here is an actual successful response,
中文字幕
which means everything is indeed OK.
And if the browser looks a little farther down in the virtual envelope,
中文字幕
if you will, it will see another language called HTML, HyperText Markup
Language, which is the stuff we wrote a couple of weeks ago
中文字幕
and you'll continue writing this week as you now dynamically generate websites.
But what we'll introduce today is what's also known as a framework,
中文字幕
or, more precisely, a microframework, because we'll see in just a few minutes
time that it can actually be really annoying and really tedious
中文字幕
to generate websites automatically using Python
if you have to write Python code alone.
中文字幕
And so humans, over the past several years,
have noticed, wow, every time I make a web application using Python,
中文字幕
I find myself typing the same lines of code
again and again just to get started, or when I'm collaborating with someone
中文字幕
else, I find that, ooh, it's a little hard to collaborate
if we're all working in the same file.
中文字幕
So humans have invented what are called frameworks.
And this is an example of code written in Python
中文字幕
but using a framework called Flask.
So whereas Bootstrap, which you've played with a little bit,
中文字幕
is a framework for CSS and JavaScript, they have some dynamic features
as well, Flask is a framework for Python that
中文字幕
just gives you some library code that you can use freely
in your own applications.
中文字幕
And it just makes it, ultimately, a little easier to get your work done
and build the thing you want to build as opposed
中文字幕
to having to reinvent the wheel again and again like people before you.
And so here is a methodology to which I alluded earlier just to have
中文字幕
a mental model for the coming weeks.
So up until now, pretty much every program
中文字幕
we've written in C and most recently in Python
you could call like controller code or controller logic or business logic.
中文字幕
Right.
It's all about getting something done logically,
中文字幕
usually in one file, maybe two files if you have another helpers.ce or header
file or whatnot.
中文字幕
But we've been writing logic.
But today and two weeks ago when we will focus
中文字幕
on web programming in HTML and CSS, there's the second part of our world.
There's like the logic that gets the interesting work done with loops,
中文字幕
and conditions, and all that.
But there's also now going to be the aesthetics,
中文字幕
the stuff that the user actually sees and the way you present your data.
So we're going to just introduce two letters of an acronym
中文字幕
today moving forward.
Anytime you start writing logical code in Python,
中文字幕
it's going to be called your controller.
It's sort of like the machine that operates your entire web application,
中文字幕
but anytime you do something more aesthetic,
we're going to call that your view code, so C and V being the letters here.
中文字幕
And this just refers to a separation of concerns.
Your logic goes in this file.
中文字幕
And your aesthetics and formatting go in this other file.
Next week, we'll introduce databases in SQL, structured query language.
中文字幕
And we'll introduce an M here, because the acronym that's
in vogue for quite some time now is MVC, though there
中文字幕
are alternatives to this mental model.
And that just means there are three different types
中文字幕
of things you should be thinking about when building an application.
But today we're going to focus on these two, controller and view.
中文字幕
And up until now, we've pretty much been doing entirely controller stuff
when writing code.
中文字幕
So the motivation, ultimately, will be to get to the point of building,
essentially, this, the freshman intramural sports website,
中文字幕
which I was the first one to make back in 1996 as a sophomore,
maybe 1997 as a junior, after having only taken CS50 and a follow
中文字幕
on class CS51.
And even though this is horrifying to see nowadays, underneath the hood
中文字幕
was a whole bunch of controller logic and a whole bunch of model code,
even though I don't think MVC existed as an acronym
中文字幕
back then till humans figured out the pattern.
But what it did have via the menu up here was a whole lot of functionality.
中文字幕
So no longer did you have to walk across campus filling out a form
and drop off a sheet of paper in an RA or a proctor's dorm room.
中文字幕
You can instead just go on the web, which all of us surely take for granted
today, fill out a web-based form.
中文字幕
And then at the time, the proctor in charge of froshims
would get an email confirming who had actually registered for a sport.
中文字幕
And eventually we added CSV files, comma separated values
files like spreadsheets, in which the data was saved.
中文字幕
Then we had this really cool tournament bracket
thing, which was all very dynamic and impressive I'm sure at the time.
中文字幕
But we'll focus on really just the fundamentals today.
So how do we get there?
中文字幕
Well, let me go ahead and open up CS50 IDE
and propose that if we want to make a website, a web
中文字幕
application really, and by application I mean something that does have logic.
By website, it's generally something that's static.
中文字幕
So that's what a web app is.
It's something that changes based on who's using it, when you're using it,
中文字幕
and what you're doing with it.
Let me go ahead, and in the most annoying tedious way possible,
中文字幕
implement a web application using Python.
So I'm going to go ahead and open a file called serve.pie to serve up a website.
中文字幕
And I'm going to go ahead and import some library code.
So from HTTP server, import something called base HTTP request handler
中文字幕
and also something called HTTP server.
And then I'm going to go ahead and use this keyword class, which
中文字幕
is HTTP server, server request, request handler, base HTTP request handler--
handler.
中文字幕
Then I'm going to go ahead and in here implement
a function called def do_GET, which implies--
中文字幕
this is a function in Python that should be called anytime a user
visits my web server via GET, the type of verb
中文字幕
that we've talked about in the context of the web.
So suppose that my only goal here is to make
中文字幕
a web-based application that for the moment just says hello world.
We know how to do this with HTML, but with HTML that's just a file.
中文字幕
Let's write a program that not just prints hello world,
but generates a web page containing hello world.
中文字幕
So the way I might do this is this.
I can literally say self, because self refers to the web server in this case.
中文字幕
And I can go ahead and send a response code of 200,
just kind of presumptuously assuming everything's
中文字幕
going to be OK in a moment.
Then I'm going to go ahead and send a header, which
中文字幕
recall, we've discussed briefly in the past,
whereby this header is going to be content type and its value
中文字幕
is going to be text HTML, which is a clue to browser
that it's receiving not a GIF, or JPEG, or something else,
中文字幕
but an actual HTML page.
And then I'm going to go ahead and say that's it for the headers.
中文字幕
I'm going to call function called end headers.
And then lastly, I'm going to use Python code
中文字幕
to dynamically generate my website.
Now, what does the website have to have?
中文字幕
Just hello world at the end of the day, but there's a whole bunch of html
we need to do in order to get to that point.
中文字幕
So I'm going to use a function called wfile write in order
to write out the following.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and write out doctype--
whoops, exclamation point doctype HTML.
中文字幕
Then let me go ahead and do the same thing, wfile.write, let me go ahead
and copy paste this moving forward, which, of course, is always
中文字幕
a bad instinct.
Then let me go ahead and output HTML lang equals en for English.
中文字幕
And notice I'm using single quotes inside my double quotes
so that Python doesn't get confused.
中文字幕
Then let me go ahead and output head tag here.
Then what comes after the head tag typically?
中文字幕
Yeah, so usually title lately.
So title will be like hello title, close the title tag.
中文字幕
And now we're going to go ahead and what comes after title?
Close head, I think, if I'm doing this right.
中文字幕
And then after this we probably have a body.
And then oh my God, this is the worst way to build a website.
中文字幕
But let's go ahead and now say something simple like hello world.
And now let's go in here and say something like body.
中文字幕
And then finally, let's go ahead and end the page and say slash HTML.
Done.
中文字幕
OK, and now I actually need to configure the server to listen on a port.
So let me go ahead and define a TCP port of 8080, which we've been using.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and define the server's address as being,
oh 0.0.0.0, which is what the IDE uses by default, like a lot of servers.
中文字幕
And then let me create the web server, HTTP server.
server_address HTTP server request handler, httpd.serve_forever.
中文字幕
OK, that is how you make a web-based application that
dynamically generates HTML.
中文字幕
In retrospect, I really regret typing all of that out because the whole point
now is to throw this code away.
中文字幕
Like, this is why frameworks exist.
If my goal quite simply at hand is to write Python code that dynamically
中文字幕
generates HTML, then calling lots of functions like write,
which is essentially the equivalent of print in this context, is just tedious.
中文字幕
I got bored writing it, I accomplished so terribly
little at the end of the day.
中文字幕
And so frameworks exist to make our lives easier.
But what's going on underneath the hood is exactly this.
中文字幕
When we start using this framework called Flask,
it's just going to make all of this automated for us.
中文字幕
It's going to make it easier to specify the IP address that you
want to run your web server on, it's going
中文字幕
to make it easier to specify the port number that you want your server
to be listening on, and it's going to make it easier
中文字幕
to respond to get requests because Flask will
take care of the implementation of some function like this one called do get.
中文字幕
So all of this is there underneath the hood,
but the flask framework gives us essentially an abstraction
中文字幕
on top of that.
So what do I actually mean by that?
中文字幕
If we want to distill this now into a simpler web application,
first let's go ahead and do this.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and open up a terminal window and let me go into my code
here and go ahead and run Python of serve.py.
中文字幕
And you'll see nothing seems to be happening just yet.
So I'm going to go to cs50 IDE web server
中文字幕
to open up a tab containing the web server that I'm now running.
And you'll see that's it.
中文字幕
That's the only thing I accomplished right now.
It's not dynamic to be sure, but there is code and Python code
中文字幕
there with which I could actually do something dynamically.
But let's instead do this now with Flask, this framework
中文字幕
that seems to make our lives easier.
I'm going to go ahead and make a program called application.py, which
中文字幕
is just a convention.
I could call it anything I want.
中文字幕
And I'm going to go ahead and say the following.
Let's first go ahead and import this framework called Flask.
中文字幕
And specifically import capitalized flask, which
is the name of the framework itself.
中文字幕
And then let me preemptively import a couple of functions
called render template and then this special global variable called request.
中文字幕
You would only know to do this from reading the documentation.
But now let me go ahead and say, hey Flask,
中文字幕
could you please give me a web application?
And this is copy paste.
中文字幕
You need this at the top of any Flask application,
and it just means turn this file--
中文字幕
application.py-- into a web application.
Then lastly, I'm going to go ahead and do this.
中文字幕
I'm going to tell Flask I want to build an app that
has a route that's listening for slash inside of that virtual envelope.
中文字幕
And whenever, Flask, you see a request for slash from some user,
go ahead and call this function which I arbitrarily called index,
中文字幕
but I could call it foo, or bar, or whatever.
And what I want you to do is this, return hello world.
中文字幕
And that's it.
So all of those other lines I tediously wrote out a moment ago
中文字幕
are now distilled into just 7 lines, which none of which
are completely obvious how they work just yet.
中文字幕
But if you assume that this means give me access to the library,
turned my file into a web application, and listen now
中文字幕
for get requests on slash, it kind of makes sense
and fits into the mental model that we introduced a couple of weeks
中文字幕
ago with HTML and CSS itself.
And to run this server, what I'm going to do now in my hello directory, which
中文字幕
is where a online copy of this is on the course's website,
I'm going to go ahead and quite simply say Flask run.
中文字幕
So Flask is not only a framework or code that you have access
to as free and open source code, but it's also
中文字幕
a program you can run at the command line that also figures out
how to turn the server on and just run it forever.
中文字幕
You're going to see some diagnostic output at first glance, most of which
you don't have to care about.
中文字幕
But there will be a few URL that's spit out which
is based on your own user name.
中文字幕
Mine today is jharvard 3 just for demonstration purposes.
And if you click on that URL and then click Open,
中文字幕
you'll see now this version of the same application doing just this.
Now, I'm kind of cheating, though.
中文字幕
Because if I open up Chrome and view my page source, notice that of course
I'm cheating because all I've done is print out hello world.
中文字幕
And if I view the source of this page, I'm
literally only going to say hello world and no actual HTML
中文字幕
because I literally didn't type out any HTML in my file.
But it turns out that Flask makes this easy, as well.
中文字幕
So let me go ahead and stop the server here for just a moment.
Control-c is your friend, it gets you out
中文字幕
of whatever program is actually running.
And let me go ahead and do this.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and not just return quote-unquote hello world
as a hardcoded value.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and return the rendering of a template called index.html.
And so this is a feature of Flask, too.
中文字幕
If you want to separate your logic--
your controller-- from your HTML--
中文字幕
your view-- you literally put the former in application.pi,
and you put the latter in an HTML file like this.
中文字幕
And you tell the controller code--
application.py-- show the user, to render
中文字幕
for the user the index.html file.
So where do I put this?
中文字幕
The convention would be to make a directory called templates.
And then in that directory, go ahead and put a file called index.html.
中文字幕
And if I go ahead and open up the file that I already
created in advance of class here, let me just show you what this looks like.
中文字幕
And then we'll take a look at it in a browser.
Here is HTML now with a pretty fancy feature
中文字幕
that we're about to reveal the utility of.
What jumps out at you is new in this file?
中文字幕
Two curly braces on the name.
Yeah, two curly braces.
中文字幕
And somehow or other that used to be saying world,
but in my final version of this I actually
中文字幕
am hinting at some more powerful capabilities.
This kind of looks like a placeholder, if you will.
中文字幕
Maybe someone's actual name.
And here's where the power of something like Flask comes into play.
中文字幕
It makes it really easy to do something like this.
So let me go ahead and actually turn this
中文字幕
into something a little more interesting.
Let me go into application.py.
中文字幕
And before I actually render this HTML file, let me go ahead and do this.
Let me go ahead and declare a variable called name.
中文字幕
And let me go ahead and check the incoming request,
the inside of that virtual envelope.
中文字幕
Let me check its arguments or any of the HTTP parameters that were passed in
and try to get something called name like this.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and save that and then notice this.
Render template takes multiple arguments.
中文字幕
The first one should be the name of the template you want to render.
But if you want to pass in data dynamically,
中文字幕
you can use named parameters in Python.
Recall from last week that you can do things like this, x equals y,
中文字幕
and z equals w.
You can pass in the names of the things you want to pass in
中文字幕
and their corresponding values.
So if I want to pass in a name variable and set it equal to the name variable
中文字幕
that I just defined, watch what we can do here.
Let me go back to my console.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and rerun in my hello directory, which is available online,
Flask run.
中文字幕
And now let me go over to this where it previously said hello world.
Let me now, just like with our Google example a couple of weeks
中文字幕
ago, type in not q equals cats, which is what we did last time,
but maybe name equals David to simulate a get request.
中文字幕
And if I did everything right, when I hit Enter I now see this dynamically.
And if I change this now from David to, say, Veronica, of course,
中文字幕
this is going to dynamically output this.
Can someone now try to break my code?
中文字幕
Propose an input that I should try to see if I messed up somewhere.
No entry.
中文字幕
OK, no input.
Or what's that?
中文字幕
say again?
Name equals name, I like that one, too.
中文字幕
So let's try that, name equals name.
So OK, I mean it's kind of maybe like a grammatical bug or semantic bug,
中文字幕
but not really a code bug per se.
That's just user error.
中文字幕
But what if I just get rid of it?
OK, that just looks a little stupid.
中文字幕
So an aesthetic bug, but we should probably start handling this.
What if I get rid of name altogether?
中文字幕
Interesting.
It seems that my final version actually has some built in functionality.
中文字幕
So where is that coming from?
Well, what if I did this?
中文字幕
It turns out that I could say something like this.
If not name, then go ahead and set name equal to world
中文字幕
would be one way of doing it.
Or I could actually use the function here.
中文字幕
Turns out that this get function can take a default value.
And so if you read the documentation, you'll
中文字幕
see that the second value you provide will be
used if the user hasn't provided one.
中文字幕
And so indeed, if I reload now and see nothing, I get world.
And if I instead do name equals, say, Brian, I get that dynamic output.
中文字幕
And so when I say web application, this is just a hint of what I mean.
This is dynamically generated content.
中文字幕
It's not hardcoded, because it's actually coming from the user.
So when Google implements its slash search web application,
中文字幕
this is the kind of thing they're doing.
It's way more involved, of course.
中文字幕
They're searching a database, looking for cats, and dogs, or whatever
it is you're searching for and then generating HTML.
中文字幕
But notice with just this simple approach
can we ourselves generate any HTML we want dynamically.
中文字幕
Because all we have to do in that template
called index.html is exactly this.
中文字幕
Hello, comma, and then a placeholder where
name is the variable you're passing in.
中文字幕
And so to be clear, it doesn't have to be called name.
I could do something like foo, which would be a little nonsensical.
中文字幕
But if I do that, the variable I plug in needs to be called foo here.
And so there's a one to one correspondence
中文字幕
between the things before the equal signs and where they get
plugged in down here.
中文字幕
Any questions, then, on this simple example, but building block?
Yeah?
中文字幕
dynamically generated.
Sure.
中文字幕
By dynamically generated, I mean I have not written in advance by typing it out
manually a web page that says hello David, or hello Brian,
中文字幕
or hello Veronica.
Those pages are all generated dynamically based on user input.
中文字幕
I wrote most of those pages.
I wrote everything up into and after the comma, but then-- sorry,
中文字幕
up to the comma, but then the names are dynamically added.
Good question.
中文字幕
Other questions?
All right.
中文字幕
So why don't we rewind to 1997 or so and see
if we can't build a more dynamic web application that actually allow
中文字幕
students to register for something that's
a little more compelling than just providing their name?
中文字幕
So let me go ahead and open up froshim0, which is the first larger scale
application we have here today.
中文字幕
And notice that I have a few files.
So already things are going to escalate quickly whereby we're
中文字幕
going to suddenly introduce multiple templates,
but we'll do this in order to solve a problem.
中文字幕
But first let me go ahead and open up application,py,
which just like your main function in C is kind of the entry point now
中文字幕
to a web-based application.
So notice that-- let's start like this.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and delete that and start from the beginning here.
Let's go ahead and do this.
中文字幕
In froshim0, we have this default route of slash,
and notice that it's going to render index.html.
中文字幕
So when you start to read someone else's code,
you kind of follow these breadcrumbs.
中文字幕
So let me go ahead and open the same folder, froshim0.
Let me go into--
中文字幕
let me go ahead, rather, let's do this from scratch, actually.
Let's do this.
中文字幕
Index.html, and let me do the familiar doctype HTML.
Then let me go ahead and do an HTML tag here, it finishes my thought for me.
中文字幕
The head tag here, the title tag here, froshim0 will be the title here.
Let me go ahead and create a body.
中文字幕
And now for this web page, I want to go ahead
and have a few things via which the user can actually register for froshim.
中文字幕
So let me go ahead and have just some title text
here, like register for froshims like I did back in the day.
中文字幕
Then let me go ahead and start a form tag.
And then in here, what information might a student
中文字幕
want to provide when registering for something like a sports team?
Name.
中文字幕
OK, the student's name.
So input type equals text.
中文字幕
The name of this input probably shouldn't be something generic like q,
it should probably be more descriptive like name.
中文字幕
So its a little weird looking, but name equals name.
And we'll go ahead and do this.
中文字幕
And if we really want to be fancy, we can
do like a placeholder text of name just to in light gray text show the user
中文字幕
what we want.
And then back in the day, minimally the students
中文字幕
registering for sports had to provide their dorm,
so the building in which they lived.
中文字幕
So in HTML, we've got a bunch of input types.
We've got text boxes, turns out there's text areas which are even bigger,
中文字幕
check boxes, radio buttons, what's most apt perhaps for choosing your dorm?
Dropdown list.
中文字幕
Like a dropdown list, otherwise called a menu.
But which tag?
中文字幕
Container?
Not a container, a little more precise than that.
中文字幕
With what tag can you generate a dropdown list
if you've done this before in HTML?
中文字幕
Select.
So it's not perfectly clearly named, but it's, indeed, a select menu by name.
中文字幕
And so I can actually do this.
Select, and the name of this field will be dorm, for instance.
中文字幕
And then inside of this I'm going to go ahead and have a few options.
So one option might be let's say Apley Court, which
中文字幕
is one of the buildings in which freshmen live.
There might be another one called Canoday,
中文字幕
and then there's going to be bunches of others.
And then notice, too, if you've never used a select menu, which you wouldn't
中文字幕
have really had occasion to yet unless you've done this
before, these options also have to have values, which for my purposes
中文字幕
are going to be exactly the same.
But whereas what's between the tags is what the human sees,
中文字幕
it's what's between these quotes as the value of value
that the computer actually sees.
中文字幕
So these are the words that populate the dropdown menu,
these are the values that actually gets stuffed into the virtual envelope
中文字幕
that the student him or herself actually see.
So let me go ahead and save this.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and now open up my console.
And I'm going to borrow a little code just so
中文字幕
that we can do this from scratch here.
So let me go ahead and grab from froshim0 my application.py file
中文字幕
and go into my workspace.
So let me go ahead now and run Flask run wherein
中文字幕
I have this application.py file.
I'm going to see the URL at which my code now lives.
中文字幕
And if I open this up, I'm going to see an internal server error.
So intended at some point because internal server error, recall,
中文字幕
was one of the more arcane status codes, 500, that you probably
have not seen unless you're visiting a website where something has actually
中文字幕
going wrong.
So how do I begin to figure out what has gone wrong now
中文字幕
that I'm actually writing code and not just writing hard coded HTML?
Well, all of the clues are going to be found
中文字幕
here inside of the console window.
So when you're running Flask you are running a full fledged web server.
中文字幕
You are listening via TCP/IP for incoming requests from users.
And so what you'll see in the console is not just the diagnostic output
中文字幕
when you first start Flask, but you're going to see all of the error messages
that might actually happen thereafter.
中文字幕
And this is a little cryptic looking.
Frankly, it's overwhelming to see this text at first glance.
中文字幕
But whereas in Clang and in C it generally
helps to look at the very top, sometimes the error messages
中文字幕
here in this context of Flask are kind of toward the bottom.
And here we have template not found.
中文字幕
Template because it can't find index.html.
And that's just because I screwed up.
中文字幕
So let me actually exit Flask by typing control-c.
And if I type ls in my directory, notice that I haven't quite
中文字幕
practiced what I've preached.
It's perhaps a little subtle, but I haven't organized myself
中文字幕
in the right way.
What have I done wrong?
中文字幕
Yeah?
Didn't make a templates directory.
中文字幕
Yeah, it's kind of a silly mistake.
I didn't make a templates directory.
中文字幕
So you can do this in a few different ways.
By the folder icon up here, you can create a new folder
中文字幕
by right clicking or control clicking.
Or in Linux you can do make dir for make directory.
中文字幕
And so I can do make dir templates enter.
And then I can move my index.html file, which
中文字幕
I wrote a moment ago, into my templates directory by just using mv for move.
And now I can go ahead and run Flask run, cross my fingers,
中文字幕
go back to the browser tab and click reload,
and voila, now I actually see the form.
中文字幕
So have these kinds of instincts.
I didn't actually intend that, but I forgot to create the folder.
中文字幕
I got this server error.
You don't have to just stare at the browser, which
中文字幕
is not going to have much information.
But if you look at the console, the terminal window
中文字幕
that you have control over will you see those clang-like error messages.
So here we have a basic HTML form.
中文字幕
It's not complete because I didn't bother typing out
all of the dorm names, but I do have an input of type text
中文字幕
as well as the Select menu.
And I'm also kind of missing a key detail, it seems.
中文字幕
What should I probably add to this form?
Where you're selecting.
中文字幕
Well, I'm selecting--
I could be selecting dorm, so I could clean this up in a couple ways.
中文字幕
I also am missing a Submit button.
Now, it turns out you could probably hit Enter
中文字幕
and it would actually be submitted by default. But we can fix this.
So let me go into index.html.
中文字幕
Let me shrink this tab just a little bit and let me fix both of these things.
So let me go ahead and open up this latest version, which
中文字幕
is now in that templates directory.
Let me go ahead and at the bottom here do an input type equals submit,
中文字幕
the value of which is going to be a register, just to make
clear to the human what's going on.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and go back to my form, click reload.
And nothing's happened just yet.
中文字幕
And that's because by default when you make changes to some of your files,
Flask is not going to notice.
中文字幕
And we'll fix this actually in the coming problem
set by adding more code and a little more
中文字幕
complexity to automate this for you.
But when in doubt, just control-c to quit flask.
中文字幕
Then go ahead and rerun flask, that will reload all
of your HTML, all of your Python code.
中文字幕
And if I now go back here and click reload, we'll see the Register button.
So there should never be any surprises.
中文字幕
And if there are, just try to get to the diagnosis thereof.
This is also a little unclear, too, to what this menu is.
中文字幕
So it turns out that if you actually create a bogus option like this
that has no value and say something like dorm, you can save this.
中文字幕
Let's go ahead and restart Flask and reload the page here.
You'll see that now you see dorm.
中文字幕
Unfortunately, this is kind of stupid because now dorm
is where you can literally live apparently,
中文字幕
which doesn't quite feel right.
So there's HTML fixes for this too.
中文字幕
I can actually go in here and technically say disabled,
so you can't actually select that.
中文字幕
Now if I rerun Flask and reload, now it still shows it there.
But because I already selected Apley Court, you can see it in gray.
中文字幕
And we can actually be a little more specific,
if you want to not only disable it, but select it by default and then go ahead
中文字幕
and reload the page here, now you'll see hopefully
what's familiar on most websites.
中文字幕
It says dorm, but it's disabled.
And even though the silly checkmark is there,
中文字幕
you're forced to choose an actual dorm.
So these are minor aesthetics, but the kind of things
中文字幕
you now have control over.
So what's going to happen?
中文字幕
I haven't actually specified where this form should
go when I actually register because I'm missing some key details on the form
中文字幕
tag.
And we haven't done this in a couple of weeks.
中文字幕
But when we were playfully reimplementing Google,
what else did we add to the form tag?
中文字幕
What attributes?
Anyone remember?
中文字幕
Yeah.
Oh, say again?
中文字幕
Action, which means what?
What to do.
中文字幕
All right, so the action we want to take,
even though this is not necessarily perfectly well named,
中文字幕
is where do you want to submit the form to?
And I could actually submit this in a few different ways.
中文字幕
I'm going to go ahead and say, you know what,
submit it to a reasonably named route slash register.
中文字幕
Google, for instance, might have code that instead says
to submit their form to slash search.
中文字幕
But we're not searching for something, we're registering.
So the name of the route is entirely up to us.
中文字幕
And via what method should we submit this information?
What are our two options?
中文字幕
Get or post.
Get tends to be the default if you don't mention in links.
中文字幕
Why might you want to use post instead?
You want it to go to a database in order to do something.
中文字幕
Yeah, you want it to go to a database and do something.
And the right verb to use there is to post information
中文字幕
as opposed to getting information.
And even more specifically when it comes to privacy, when you use post,
中文字幕
the information doesn't end up in the user's URL,
and therefore doesn't end up in his or her history,
中文字幕
and therefore doesn't end up in a place that siblings, or roommates, or anyone
else can actually see just by poking around.
中文字幕
So we'll, indeed, go ahead, because this is my name, and dorm, and maybe
my phone number, and email, and credit card number,
中文字幕
and the like on some other website.
I'm going to use post for that instead.
中文字幕
So the catch here is that this week, we now
have the ability to implement slash register.
中文字幕
Two weeks ago we could just send people to Google's slash search,
but now we have the ability to make our own routes.
中文字幕
But how many routes have we defined thus far in application.py?
Just the one.
中文字幕
And again, some new syntax with the funky at sign and the route
keyword here.
中文字幕
But let me actually just intuitively guess
that if I go ahead and say app.route slash register,
中文字幕
I bet I could implement a second route and tell the web server
to listen in two places, on slash as well as on slash register.
中文字幕
But if I wanted to listen specifically on post, it actually has to be this.
Methods equals quote-unquote post.
中文字幕
Because by default just for convenience, it assumes only gets.
So I need to add that.
中文字幕
You'd only know that from the documentation.
Now I'm going to go ahead and define a function.
中文字幕
This is slightly an annoying feature of Flask.
You have to give the function a name even though you'll probably
中文字幕
never reference it anywhere.
So I'm going to go ahead and just reasonably call this register.
中文字幕
And now I have a to do.
What am I going to want to do when the user clicks that Submit button?
中文字幕
Store it.
I want to store it somewhere.
中文字幕
So I probably want to store it.
But what might I want to do first before he or she is actually
中文字幕
allowed to register, even though they've clicked that submit form?
Maybe confirm their information, right?
中文字幕
Because if a lazy user comes in, or if a user accidentally clicks the button
or hits enter, they might actually submit nothing-- no name, no dorm.
中文字幕
That's not useful information.
It could just be perceived as spam.
中文字幕
So we probably want to ask some kind of logical question
like if they didn't give us a name or they didn't give us a dorm,
中文字幕
yell at the user in some way.
So I'm going to go ahead and do that.
中文字幕
So let me actually express this in Python,
kind of like we did last week with some error checking.
中文字幕
So recall that the user's name can be gotten from an HTTP parameter.
From the request.args get, and then ask for the name parameter.
中文字幕
Their dorm, meanwhile, can come from request.args get dorm.
And again, this request.args is something
中文字幕
we gave ourselves access to up here when we said, hey Flask,
please give me access to the user's request, that virtual envelope.
中文字幕
Request.arg refers to all of the HTTP parameters in the URL.
And get is just a function or a method built into that special Flask
中文字幕
feature that allows us to get a specific parameter like name,
or dorm, or anything else.
中文字幕
And recall that in Python, what's kind of nice is that you can say pretty
English-like, if not name or not--
中文字幕
not dorm, let's go ahead and reprimand the user.
For instance, we could say failure because he or she did not actually
中文字幕
cooperate as we intended.
Otherwise if they did cooperate, I'm going
中文字幕
to go ahead and render template success.
And we'll flesh this out in just a moment.
中文字幕
So I've got two scenarios handled.
If they didn't cooperate or if they did, render quote-unquote failure
中文字幕
or a full fledged HTML template.
So now that I've implemented slash register and I'm listening for a route
中文字幕
by a post, let's go ahead and reload the page for good measure.
Type in my name.
中文字幕
Not going to tell you my dorm, but you're going to notice as much.
OK, so now the server has noticed that I didn't actually cooperate and provide
中文字幕
both a name and a dorm.
And so it's returning to me just quote-unquote failure.
中文字幕
So that's good because now I know, all right, I did something wrong clearly.
Let me go back let me go ahead and maybe do Canaday here.
中文字幕
And now let me go ahead and register.
But, but, but, but, this I know in advance is going to err.
中文字幕
Why?
I don't have a success.html.
中文字幕
OK, so let's preemptively address this.
Let me actually go in here to my templates directory.
中文字幕
I'm going to go ahead and create a new file called success.html.
Let me go into the templates to save it there.
中文字幕
And you know what, success can be a pretty simple page.
And let me open my index page, let me copy that, let me go into success,
中文字幕
let me paste this.
Let me get rid of all of that body and just say success, for instance.
中文字幕
So let me now go ahead and go restart Flask,
because I've made a new template.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and reload the form just for good measure.
Let me go ahead and give you my name this time, and OK, I live in Canaday,
中文字幕
and register.
And what did I do wrong this time?
中文字幕
So it turns out you can't do it this way, obviously.
[LAUGHTER] So when you're actually submitting information to
中文字幕
via a form via get, Flask very cleverly puts
that information in a different place.
中文字幕
Because by definition, as I claim very correctly earlier,
in request.args are all of the key value pairs
中文字幕
that are in the URL that are coming in from the user's request.
But when you submit via post, for reasons I wish were now otherwise
中文字幕
you actually have to access those values via a different variable.
So instead of using request.args, you have to use request.form both here
中文字幕
and here to make clear-- and this is horribly named for exactly the reasons
that I think I'm tripping over here--
中文字幕
because they actually are both coming in via a form, via a get or post.
But Flask puts get arguments in args and puts post arguments in form.
中文字幕
Thereby leading clearly to potential confusion.
But if I go ahead now and load this version of the site and I keep hoping,
中文字幕
I'm going to go ahead now run Flask, restart this page, type in David,
give you my dorm, and register and successfully register for froshim.
中文字幕
See how easy web programming is?
So hopefully now we can at least focus on the structure of what I've done
中文字幕
and now begin to improve it.
Because notice that I kind of did not practice what I preached a moment ago.
中文字幕
What habit did I violate when I whipped up success.html?
How did I get to that point?
中文字幕
Yeah?
Copy and paste.
中文字幕
Yeah, I copied and paste.
Which again, usually in programming not the right thing to do.
中文字幕
Might get the job done super fast, but it's probably the wrong instinct,
because it's going to get harder and harder to maintain.
中文字幕
Now, why is that?
You've played HTML a couple of weeks ago.
中文字幕
And recall from that problem set when you had to make a home page,
you probably found yourselves copying and pasting across your two,
中文字幕
or three, or four pages because you wanted them to kind of look the same.
And therefore it made sense for them to have some commonalities.
中文字幕
But in HTML alone, there was no way to say use the same layout for my whole
site-- use the same color scheme, the same fonts, the same CSS--
中文字幕
but just change the body of the page for each individual page.
And so some of you very rightly on discourse and beyond like
中文字幕
posted questions asking, could you do this?
And you can't really in HTML alone.
中文字幕
But now that we have access to Python, an actual programming language
they can do things logically, now you can actually
中文字幕
start to factor those things out, too.
And notice in this file, success.html, as well as in index.html,
中文字幕
what are some of the commonalities, suffice it to say?
The form is only in one of them, but what
中文字幕
else is obviously redundant everywhere?
The title, the head of the page more generally, the doctype at the very top,
中文字幕
the body tag alone.
And you could imagine there'd be even more details like from your own home
中文字幕
pages that you wanted to be the same across multiple pages.
So let's actually take a look at a refactorization of this code,
中文字幕
the one I did write in advance in froshim0,
and you'll see why it actually makes sense
中文字幕
to have not only multiple files, each of which
represents one of your routes or your views,
中文字幕
but also to have this file called layout.html.
In Flask, when building a web application that you know
中文字幕
is going to follow a certain structural pattern, commonalities
across all of your pages, you can actually do this.
中文字幕
So in this file here, layout.html is a whole bunch of hardcoded HTML.
And it's pretty simple.
中文字幕
It's got my HTML tag, head tag, title tag, body tag, and a few other things,
but that's the general structure of the page.
中文字幕
And notice it has this funky syntax in the middle.
In white here is what's called the block.
中文字幕
This is now Flask specific.
Just like Flask supports those two curly braces on the left
中文字幕
and the right that says put a value here, flask
also supports this other notation, curly brace percent and percent curly
中文字幕
brace that actually allows you to put placeholders for actual chunks of HTML.
Not just variables, but actual chunks of HTML.
中文字幕
And so this layout you can think of as a mold or a template
literally that all of your other pages are going to be structured based on,
中文字幕
but they are going to vary in this line and only this line.
And we're going to put as much HTML between the body tags as we want,
中文字幕
the open and the close tag.
This just indicates to Flask this is the stuff that should be changing.
中文字幕
So if I now look at my index.html, which recall earlier
contained my form index.html.
中文字幕
Notice that here's the form, and I finished it earlier.
I went ahead and typed out all of the freshman dorms,
中文字幕
not just the two of them.
And you'll see that the file starts almost the same
中文字幕
and then continues with more stuff.
But notice what's missing from index.html this time.
中文字幕
No doctype.
No HTML tag.
中文字幕
No head tag, no title tag, no body tag.
All of the common stuff has been factored out.
中文字幕
But there's some funky new syntax that, again, is Flask specific.
This first line is the link between this file and the layout.
中文字幕
That first line says, hey Flask, this index.html file
extends the definition of layout.html.
中文字幕
So it says grab that template and plug myself in there.
What do you want to plug in?
中文字幕
The same syntax here.
When you actually put stuff between the block tag
中文字幕
and the end block tag, which is down below, that's when you say to Flask,
go ahead and take this stuff and plug it into the placeholder in the layout.
中文字幕
So meanwhile, the success page also now can be a little more sophisticated.
If I go into success, it's not very complicated.
中文字幕
And honestly, it doesn't even look like HTML
anymore because we're using these more dynamic features.
中文字幕
But this just says, hey Flask, use the same layout
so the page is structured exactly the same.
中文字幕
But for the body, go ahead and plug in this value instead.
So indeed, when you go ahead and load this success message,
中文字幕
you see this message here-- not just success,
I expounded here and said you are registered.
中文字幕
Well, not really, that's because there's no database yet.
But that's going to generate a full fledged HTML page.
中文字幕
And what about failure?
Before I was just cheating and just saying return failure,
中文字幕
quote-unquote, no HTML at all.
The failure page is going to be almost the same,
中文字幕
but now I can actually provide some descriptive text.
This body just says you must provide your name and dorm,
中文字幕
thereby admonishing the user for not having cooperated properly.
So now your home pages, if you kind of extrapolate from this,
中文字幕
could have the exact same layout, aesthetics and menu bars,
and all of that fanciness, but only the content would have to change.
中文字幕
And you can get out of the business of just copying and pasting.
So there, too, to your question earlier about dynamism,
中文字幕
the dynamism doesn't have to just come from the user.
It can also come from the construction dynamically of a website
中文字幕
based on multiple pages.
So at the end of the day, the browser has
中文字幕
no idea that Python exists, has no familiarity with Flask.
All the browser still sees is an HTML page.
中文字幕
But what Flask and in turn Python are doing
for us is constructing that page dynamically, following
中文字幕
the rules from two weeks to go in HTML and CSS,
and following last week's rules on how Python works.
中文字幕
Questions?
So even though
中文字幕
It's not.
Good question.
中文字幕
This new syntax, the double curly braces that we saw earlier and now
the curly brace percent signs, this is actually yet another language
中文字幕
called jinja--
J-I-N-J-A-- which is a templating language.
中文字幕
And there's dozens of these things in the world, people just come up
with their own syntax.
中文字幕
And the reason for the funky syntax is that the author of jinja
presumably could think of no other language that
中文字幕
uses like a curly brace and a percent sign
and a percent sign and a curly brace.
中文字幕
And so therefore they decided, you know what,
I'm going to use this syntax because it will look distinct from HTML,
中文字幕
and CSS, and Python So that frameworks like Flask
don't confuse it with something else.
中文字幕
So do you have to upload that into ,, or is it automatic?
It's automatically supported.
中文字幕
So Flask by default supports jinja.
It could have come up with its own templating syntax.
中文字幕
But whoever invented Flask decided I don't need to reinvent this wheel,
someone else already made a templating language
中文字幕
that gives me this functionality.
So I'm going to combine our works into one.
中文字幕
And I didn't call it a language a moment ago,
because frankly, HTML, CSS, Python, JavaScript--
中文字幕
I mean, we're already running out of fingers here.
But jinja is, indeed, yet another language.
中文字幕
It's just not a programming language per se,
though it will have some control flow features
中文字幕
that we'll see in a little bit.
It's just much more limited than Python.
中文字幕
Other questions?
Is it possible to combine the success and failure HTML
中文字幕
files into one just for better design?
Good question.
中文字幕
Could you combine the success and the failure pages into one?
Short answer, yes.
中文字幕
And let me not show it yet, because it'll get a little more complicated.
But yes, I could imagine passing a variable in that's a Boolean--
中文字幕
true or false--
into just one of these templates.
中文字幕
And maybe I call the new template result.html.
I can actually then have an if condition in my template that
中文字幕
says if the result is true, say this.
Else if the result is false, say this other thing.
中文字幕
So you could do that, yes.
Generally, though, it's probably cleaner to keep messaging separate
中文字幕
if they functionally do something else.
After all, these files are pretty small anyway.
中文字幕
Yeah?
Just for question, what does the user
中文字幕
see if they were to open up the debugging console on Chrome
and look at at it, what do they see as the HTML that shows up?
中文字幕
Really good question.
What does the user see?
中文字幕
We can answer this by just literally opening Chrome and opening
View Page Source or the Inspector.
中文字幕
This is what the browser sees.
So when I claimed earlier that the browser has no idea of Python or Flask
中文字幕
are even involved, that is, indeed, true.
Because what browser's receiving at the end of the day
中文字幕
is just this, the dynamically constructed HTML.
Good question.
中文字幕
Yeah?
can you also put Python code in there,
中文字幕
or is it just HTML?
Good question.
中文字幕
We'll see more of this in just a little bit.
The question is, can you between the curly brace and percent signs
中文字幕
put actual Python code?
You can put stuff that looks like Python code, but not all of Python.
中文字幕
And so more of that in a bit.
Is there a function call or something like that?
中文字幕
Only certain functions.
Templating languages, long story short, are sandbox so
中文字幕
that they are not as expressive as a real programming language.
Otherwise you are vulnerable to potential hacks.
中文字幕
You want their functionality to be very limited because they're
only about displaying data, not about thinking or doing logic generally.
中文字幕
More on that in a bit.
All right, that was a lot all at once.
中文字幕
Let's take a five minute break here, turn on some music, come back,
and we'll make this act better.
中文字幕
All right, we are back.
So to recap where froshim0 left off, we now
中文字幕
have this structure which is pretty much conventional.
Any web application we make here on out is
中文字幕
going to follow this pattern of having an application.py entry point where
all the interesting stuff starts, a layout.html file
中文字幕
in your templates directory that lays out
the whole site and any commonalities, and then one or more other pages that
中文字幕
actually represent your individual views that correspond to one or more
of your actual routes.
中文字幕
So now we're at the point of a stable baseline,
but had we dived in right to this, it would perhaps not make as much sense
中文字幕
as to why we did this various factorization.
So let's now improve this.
中文字幕
Because of course, if you look at success.html,
it just claims you are registered.
中文字幕
Well, not really.
Because in application.py, did we do anything with the user's information?
中文字幕
No.
We just checked, did they give us information?
中文字幕
And if so, we claim success.
Else if they missed their name and/or their dorm, we just claimed failure.
中文字幕
So what might a data structure be in Python
where we could store registrants?
中文字幕
We don't have databases yet, we don't have SQL yet.
That's a week ahead.
中文字幕
Array.
Yeah, we could use an array, otherwise known
中文字幕
as a list in Python.
So let me propose how we might do this.
中文字幕
Let me actually open up froshims1 for our second iteration of this program.
And in application.py, notice this.
中文字幕
At the very top of the file, not only am I
creating my application using the same line as before,
中文字幕
and I've commented things this time in advance using the hash symbol,
notice that I claim that on line 6 and 7 here, here
中文字幕
is an empty list for all of the students who have registered.
This way we can keep the information around.
中文字幕
And we only did this briefly last time, but does anyone
remember how you add something to a list in Python?
中文字幕
By what function?
Append.
中文字幕
So if you have .append at the end of a list's name,
you can add something to it.
中文字幕
So where is that going to go?
Well, here is my route for slash, implies, again, get by default.
中文字幕
That's the default route that a human might get,
and they are going to see index.html, which contains that form.
中文字幕
If I scroll down now, you'll see that I have a register route just like before.
But I'm doing one additional step.
中文字幕
Which is the new line here, to be clear?
Yeah, 26.
中文字幕
So I could implement this in any number of ways.
But the key detail is that I reference the list name-- students,
中文字幕
but I could have called it anything.
.append, as someone proposed, is how you add something to the end of the list.
中文字幕
And then I can add anything I want.
To keep it simple, I'm just going to add a string.
中文字幕
And I'm going to keep it super simple and just
say the string is so-and-so from such and such a dorm.
中文字幕
So David from Matthews Hall, or Brian from wherever.
And so here we have placeholders using f strings in Python.
中文字幕
So this has nothing to do with Flask, this
has nothing to do with jinja or anything we just talked about.
中文字幕
This has to do everything with last week's syntax in Python alone.
So this appends to that list this name from this dorm.
中文字幕
So let's go ahead now and try this version out.
If I go into my source sub and directory for today's code into froshims1
中文字幕
and run flask run, we'll see a URL that I can now visit.
Let me go ahead and open that for froshims1.
中文字幕
Notice that I have that complete dropdown now.
Let me go ahead and say David, but I'm not going to tell you my dorm
中文字幕
yet and try to register.
Now I see a more friendly message, not just failure.
中文字幕
And that's because of my new and improved template.
OK, I'll go ahead and be David, and I'll be from Matthews here.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and register and voila.
Now we see David from Matthews has registered.
中文字幕
And it seems to be all of a sudden in the form of a new bulleted list.
But where did that actually come from?
中文字幕
Well, I don't know.
Let me try this again.
中文字幕
Let me go back to slash, which is the route that gives me the form.
Let me go ahead and type in not David this time, but say, Brian.
中文字幕
And Brian, which dorm are you in?
Pennypacker.
中文字幕
So let me choose this from the menu instead and click Register.
And now we see Brian from Pennypacker.
中文字幕
So somehow the application is changing state,
and notice the URL that we're at is called slash registrants.
中文字幕
So that seems to be a third route this time that apparently is not interactive
per se, it just spits out the list of registered students.
中文字幕
So let's just put the proverbial engineering hat on.
If we go about implementing this slash registrants route,
中文字幕
logically what must that code be doing in verbal pseudocode, if you will?
A for loop?
中文字幕
Like a for loop, iterating over what?
In the list that saves all the registrants.
中文字幕
Yeah.
Iterating over the list of students which
中文字幕
contains all of those registrants.
And the template, meanwhile, probably has like an LI tag for list item
中文字幕
and a UL tag for unordered list, which gives me the bulleted list.
So let's take a look at that.
中文字幕
So how do we follow these breadcrumbs?
Well, if I scroll up in application.py, we'll
中文字幕
see a route called slash registrants.
And you'll see that all it does apparently
中文字幕
is it returns a template called registered.html,
where registered.html is probably a template that is generating that list.
中文字幕
But there's something different this time.
I'm passing in an argument.
中文字幕
And we saw this earlier.
When I wanted to pass in name equals David or name equals Brian,
中文字幕
I just grabbed that from a variable.
This time I'm not doing request.args, I'm not doing request.form.
中文字幕
Because what is students?
Where did this come from?
中文字幕
That's the list from higher up.
Recall that we have this global variable at the top of the program, students,
中文字幕
which is initialized to an empty list.
But recall that we keep appending to it in my register route.
中文字幕
So I can go ahead and say, you know what?
Go ahead and pass into register.html a template-- or rather, a list--
中文字幕
called students whose value is exactly that.
And again, it's stupid looking that you have the same word on the left
中文字幕
and the right of the variable name.
You could do this differently.
中文字幕
Again, you could say foo, you could say x, or y, or anything.
But frankly, it tends to make most sense, just pass
中文字幕
in the same name as the variable that you care about so that the template can
see exactly that.
中文字幕
So what's the next breadcrumb?
If I want to understand exactly what is happening,
中文字幕
what file should I open up next perhaps?
Probably register.html.
中文字幕
So let's go in there.
It's in my templates directory by definition,
中文字幕
and you'll see, indeed, a failure message which allows me to error check.
Index, which contains the form; layout, which contains the overall structure;
中文字幕
and finally, registered.html.
And now we can answer the question that you asked earlier about Python code
中文字幕
in the template.
So this one looks more advanced than before,
中文字幕
but notice it follows a pattern.
Register.html extends that same layout.
中文字幕
So it borrows from that same mold, so it looks the same.
The body of this page, though, is just this snippet of HTML.
中文字幕
Give me an unordered list, open and closed, and this
is what you can do now with jinja.
中文字幕
Again, it's almost identical to Python, so you
don't have to worry about thinking about learning yet another language.
中文字幕
It's just a subset of Python essentially.
So if I want to output in the list of all of the students,
中文字幕
I use my jinja syntax here, my template syntax with curly brace percent.
And I say for student and students.
中文字幕
Just like in Python, that induces an iteration over that list.
And then what do I want to output?
中文字幕
Well, we can borrow our curly braces from our name example
and just do list item, plug in the name of the student, close list item.
中文字幕
And then endfor.
So this is the one stupid thing with the templates.
中文字幕
Whereas in Python proper, recall that you can just
say for student in students, you have a colon
中文字幕
and then indentation handles everything.
The problem with that in the world of HTML
中文字幕
is that browsers recall ignore all whitespace,
like whitespace has no special significance, but in Python it does.
中文字幕
So the way people solve this is you literally,
if a little weirdly, say endfor--
中文字幕
one word, no space.
And that's it.
中文字幕
And indentation helps you read something like this.
So what is the HTML I'm getting back?
中文字幕
I can actually look at this.
Let me go ahead and view page source in Chrome,
中文字幕
and you'll see it's not quite as pretty as might be ideal
because there's a lot of whitespace which comes from those templates
中文字幕
from my having pretty printed those, as well.
But this is syntactically correct, and I'm dynamically putting
中文字幕
this part inside of this layout.
Any questions, then, on this?
中文字幕
So if we restart the server, whatever's stored
in the list, that goes away, right?
中文字幕
Good question.
Let's kill Flask with control-c.
中文字幕
Let's rerun the server.
And let me go back to my registrants route and reload.
中文字幕
And sadly, yes, this is not the best way to register students for a sport.
Because if the server ever goes offline, loses power, you hit control-c,
中文字幕
you obviously, indeed, lose everyone.
And notice, too, even though we've generally
中文字幕
frowned upon using global variables, which this students list indeed
is, why did I define it up here in line 7 and not,
中文字幕
for instance, in my register route here?
Because indeed, I'm appending to the list here.
中文字幕
But I very deliberately did not declare the list there.
Yeah?
中文字幕
You're using it in other parts.
I'm using it elsewhere in my other routes, the registrants route.
中文字幕
And also even more to the point, if I declared a list here,
it becomes by definition a local variable.
中文字幕
Which means as soon as this function exits,
now I've just thrown away those students who register immediately not
中文字幕
even after a control-c.
So this was a better approach to do it, but it's not
中文字幕
what I did way back in my day.
I actually did something that was a little fancier.
中文字幕
So at the time, I didn't really know-- at least in,
what, 1997-- anything about databases.
中文字幕
I don't think I even knew about CSV files just yet, or at least
how to create them dynamically.
中文字幕
So I instead took this approach.
Let me go into froshims2, and it has noticed the same templates as before.
中文字幕
And indeed, I pretty much copied and pasted for this second example.
But in application.py, notice this fanciness.
中文字幕
So here I have almost the same thing up top in terms of Flask,
but I'm also using this OS library, more on that in a bit.
中文字幕
But what about line 2?
It's subtle, but I rattled this acronym off I think just once weeks ago, SMTP.
中文字幕
Does anyone know what that stands for?
Simple mail transfer protocol?
中文字幕
Yeah, simple mail transfer protocol-- email, that is.
So Python comes with built in functionality
中文字幕
via which you can send emails, and this is exactly what I
did when I first made this website.
中文字幕
Didn't know anything about databases, I didn't know anything
about saving things to files just yet, I was still learning.
中文字幕
But I didn't realize, hm, I could use programming
to send an email to the proctor or the RA who was overseeing the sports
中文字幕
program so that they could just save it in a folder
and know who had registered.
中文字幕
It's not super user friendly, but it at least
got the job done because they were then able to track everything.
中文字幕
So in this program, notice that I have my route for my form.
And I have this register route but a few new lines of code.
中文字幕
And you would only know how to do this by reading the documentation.
But in this case here, notice what I'm doing in my register route.
中文字幕
I'm first getting the user's name and their email this time and their dorm.
Then I'm error checking.
中文字幕
If they didn't give me a name, or their email, or the dorm,
render failure.html to apprise them as much.
中文字幕
Then go ahead and do these lines of code.
And this is more of a mouthful, and you would only, again,
中文字幕
know this from the documentation.
But it turns out if you read the documentation
中文字幕
for this SMTP lib or library, you can use lines of code like this as follows.
You can tell the library what server to use for sending email.
中文字幕
And it turns out if you read Gmail's documentation,
you can use smtp.gmail.com to automatically send e-mails not using
中文字幕
the web UI, but using code.
587 is the TCP port that they use.
中文字幕
So it's not 80, it's not 443, it's 587 by convention.
Starttls, if you read the documentation, says turn on encryption.
中文字幕
So the email is encrypted between you and Gmail.
Then go ahead and log in with a certain username and password.
中文字幕
I created an account in advance called jharvard@cs50.net, and my password
is in my IDE's environment.
中文字幕
I stored it elsewhere so that it's not visible on screen,
otherwise people could send emails as John.
中文字幕
Then I go ahead and call literally a function called send mail.
And if you read the documentation, this one
中文字幕
takes as argument who you want to send email to,
the contents of the email that you want to send,
中文字幕
and the message that you actually want to send here.
Or rather, this is the from address, the to address,
中文字幕
and the actual message that you want to send.
After that, you just go ahead and render template and assume success.
中文字幕
I could add more error checking, like I should probably
check if anything went wrong here, but I'm keeping it simple.
中文字幕
But these new lines that are highlighted actually send an email.
So let's try this.
中文字幕
Let me go into froshims2 and let me go ahead and do Flask run.
Let me go ahead and open up the page here, slash.
中文字幕
And notice I do, indeed, have a second field for text now.
So this will be David, and this will be--
中文字幕
let's see, how about let's go ahead and just register not myself,
since it's not my email account, but John Harvard who we claim's
中文字幕
email is cs50.net, jharvard thereat.
And he lives in say, Weld.
中文字幕
Let's go ahead and click Register.
All right, it's taking a little longer this time,
中文字幕
but it was doing a little more work sending an email.
So now let's try to go to gmail.com, open this up.
中文字幕
Ooh.
In my inbox, you are registered.
中文字幕
If I open this up, notice jharvard@cs50.net
has sent me an email by a BC seed, at least keep part of the information
中文字幕
private.
And it just says in the body of the message if I move the cursor,
中文字幕
you are registered.
So I did a little more back in 1997, but I
中文字幕
included like the user's name, and their email address, and their dorm,
and maybe their phone number or whatnot, and the sports they were interested in.
中文字幕
But the idea is exactly that.
You can send any information you want just by now using code.
中文字幕
You could not do that with HTML or with CSS alone.
Any questions, then, on this?
中文字幕
Yeah?
Last week when we wrote code in Python we had to like
中文字幕
say if name equals the function to like execute that.
How come in this we're not doing that?
中文字幕
That was all in JavaScript.
So that allusion to if name equals, and then you assign it to a function,
中文字幕
I think you're referring to our JavaScript examples, no?
OK.
中文字幕
So we'll actually come back to that in a little bit
where we reintroduce a bit of JavaScript,
中文字幕
which actually gives us some more functionality reminiscent
of those examples.
中文字幕
Other question?
What email address did you send that email from,
中文字幕
and don't you need to enter like a password to make sure
that no one just randomly sends email?
中文字幕
Yeah, it's a really good question.
So via what email address did I send that, and to whom was it sent?
中文字幕
So again, this is the from address, this is the to address,
and this is now the message.
中文字幕
And just because I only have one email account open, I had John send himself
an email in this case.
中文字幕
Theoretically if I were running the freshmen intramural sports program,
I could try to do this and change this from address to be myself.
中文字幕
The catch is that Gmail actually has protections in place so that if you've
logged in as jharvard with his password, then
中文字幕
the email, no matter what you specify as the from address,
is actually going to be overridden to be from John Harvard.
中文字幕
However, this does speak to the potential insecurity of email.
If you don't use Gmail but you use a third party
中文字幕
service that is not so rigorous with its error checking,
it is incredibly easy to fake emails from one person to another.
中文字幕
I mean, look through your spam folder sometime.
Most of those people who send you those spams don't exist.
中文字幕
Like, the email addresses and/or the names are fake.
And yet they might appear to actually be from a sibling of yours, a family
中文字幕
member, or a friend, even though those humans did not send e-mails.
And that's because some spammer has written code
中文字幕
like this in Python or some other language,
but has overridden these fields, but used a server that's not Gmail
中文字幕
that doesn't enforce these policies.
Other questions?
中文字幕
Fun fact, also in 1995, I learned how to send--
or how to change the from address on an email.
中文字幕
And turns out at Harvard there's this entity called the ad
board who doesn't like doing this.
中文字幕
So don't do that.
Sometimes there's human defenses in place for this, not just technological.
中文字幕
Thankfully, my friend whom I faked an email from did not--
it worked out OK.
中文字幕
All right.
You have now great power, don't use it for evil.
中文字幕
All right, so let's go ahead now and do another example, but that takes this
a further step, adding, finally some persistence of information.
中文字幕
Let's go ahead into froshims3 now and open up application.py.
So recall that we can use CSV files-- comma separated value files--
中文字幕
to create the illusion of like spreadsheets,
but now we're actually going to create them ourselves.
中文字幕
The code for this is a little more involved,
and the only thing I've changed now really is the register method.
中文字幕
So in version one of this code, I saved it in a global list just in memory.
That was not good because it gets thrown away too easily.
中文字幕
Version two of this we just sent an email
to the proctor who runs the program.
中文字幕
That was a little better, because at least they can then save the email.
Version three, we're going to use a very lightweight database called
中文字幕
the CSV file that saves it to my hard drive permanently.
So even when the server stops, the data is still there.
中文字幕
So in Python, how does this work?
Well, notice that I've improved my register route this time as follows.
中文字幕
If the user did not give me their name or dorm,
then I go ahead and render a failure.
中文字幕
That's pretty much the same logic as before,
but I didn't bother declaring the variables this time,
中文字幕
I just called the functions directly.
Here's a new line of code that might be reminiscent of some of your past file
中文字幕
I/O code.
In line 16 here, I'm telling Python to go ahead and open a file called
中文字幕
registered.csv quote-unquote a.
So we've seen R, we've seen W for read and write.
中文字幕
Anyone recall what a is, or no?
Append.
中文字幕
It happens to mean append, which means just
add a row to the file, which is nice.
中文字幕
Because if there's already students registered, when a new one registers
we just want to append to the bottom of the file.
中文字幕
Quote-unquote a is supported by Python with this open function.
That gives me back a reference or like a pointer to file,
中文字幕
even though Python does not have pointers.
Then this is the new feature.
中文字幕
And here, too, you'd only know this from having seen an example
or you reading the documentation.
中文字幕
You can use the CSV library, which we'll see as imported up above.
And you can ask for a writer, a piece of code that writes out-- that is,
中文字幕
creates--
CSV files.
中文字幕
And specifically, you want to write to this file.
That library-- the CSV library-- comes with a function
中文字幕
called write row, which does what it says.
If you pass it in a comma separated list of fields
中文字幕
that you want to represent your first column, your second column,
and your third column, it will handle the writing for you
中文字幕
so you don't have to get into the weeds of file I/O
like you did several problem sets ago.
中文字幕
Notice the subtlety.
You do need to have these second pair of parentheses,
中文字幕
because technically what you're giving it is a tuple.
We talked very briefly about that last week,
中文字幕
which is just like an x comma y pair, or latitude comma longitude.
Same idea here.
中文字幕
First column, second column, and so forth is a so-called tuple.
Then I close the file, then I render the template.
中文字幕
So what does this actually do for me?
Well, let me go into my folder froshims3 here.
中文字幕
And notice register.csv at the moment is empty.
This is a CSV file.
中文字幕
Nothing's going on inside of that.
There's no one registered yet.
中文字幕
But let me go ahead, then, and go into froshims3, run Flask run.
Let me go ahead and load this up.
中文字幕
And you'll see the same kind of form, but also a new link.
Notice that no one's registered yet if I click on that link.
中文字幕
But if I go into here and register David from Matthews and click Register,
now it claims I am registered really.
中文字幕
Let me click this link and notice that it's very small on the screen,
but slash registered is where this is going to lead
中文字幕
me, which is just where I was before.
You see that now David from Matthews registered.
中文字幕
Let me go back to the form itself.
Let's register, say, Brian from Pennypacker.
中文字幕
Click Register.
He, too, is apparently registered.
中文字幕
Let's click that link.
Brian from Pennypacker.
中文字幕
All right, so where is this data going?
Let me go back to the IDE, close my registered CSV file,
中文字幕
because it's probably changed and open it up.
And voila, indeed, it's prompting me to reload it.
中文字幕
There is the file.
And notice David comma Matthews, Brian comma Pennypacker, all of those rows
中文字幕
were written out for me.
So now I actually have a database.
中文字幕
And even though it's kind of a simple database, you know what I can do?
Let me go ahead and right click or control click on it in the IDE,
中文字幕
download it into my Downloads folder.
And then if I actually open this thing, if I
中文字幕
have Excel installed or Apple Numbers, which
is the first time I've ever used it, let me go ahead and open that file.
中文字幕
Opening register.csv.
And voila, here now is a file.
中文字幕
And Numbers is formatting it in kind of a funky way,
but it is showing rows and columns.
中文字幕
Those of you who are more familiar with Excel we can do that, too.
Let me go down here.
中文字幕
Let me go into my Downloads folder.
Control click or right click here, and this time open it with Microsoft Excel.
中文字幕
And if you've seen Excel before, we'll probably see a very similar UI.
Because anytime Excel or Numbers--
中文字幕
OK, first time I've used Excel.
So that, too, will open up some rows and columns, as well.
中文字幕
So CSV files are just very lightweight spreadsheets.
But what's cool about them is that you can create them so easily.
中文字幕
You just have to put commas in there.
Now, as an aside, can you contrive a user's input
中文字幕
that could potentially break a CSV file?
What could a human type in that could potentially break your own CSV files?
中文字幕
A comma, right?
If it's like David Mayland comma junior, or something like that.
中文字幕
Or anything with weird punctuation.
This is why you use libraries.
中文字幕
That CSV library in this code, which we're
importing at the very top of this version 3 of the code,
中文字幕
is actually handling all of that complexity for us.
When the library encounters David Mayland comma junior if that's
中文字幕
the user's input, it will then additionally
put quotes around my whole name, thereby making sure
中文字幕
that my comma is inside quotes and not, therefore,
confused with the special comma that demarcates the start of other columns.
中文字幕
So again, that's why you don't reinvent the wheel,
because corner cases like that arise.
中文字幕
Well, what about slash registered, which is this list that's
generating an unordered list?
中文字幕
Let's see how that works.
If I scroll down to this code, notice that it's not
中文字幕
just a simple matter of grabbing a global variable,
because there is no global variable anymore.
中文字幕
Now I have to read it from that CSV file.
So here's three new lines of code that work as follows.
中文字幕
I'm going to go ahead and open this file, register.csv, in Read mode
this time, not append.
中文字幕
I'm going to go ahead now and say hey Python, use the CSV reader--
which is the opposite of writer--
中文字幕
on that file.
And then, hey Python, go ahead and turn that whole reader into a list.
中文字幕
So you'd only know this from reading the documentation.
It turns out this is the recommendation.
中文字幕
If you want to take a reader and just read the whole thing into memory
at once and convert it to a Python list, you literally just pass it
中文字幕
to this list function.
That gives me a list I'm going to call students,
中文字幕
and then I can do my same code as before.
For good measure, I should probably do what
中文字幕
I did last time, which is file.close to close the file, as well, just
to make sure it's closed the next time it's opened.
中文字幕
But I can actually simplify this, and you'll see more of these examples
online.
中文字幕
It's actually more conventional in Python not to do this,
but instead to change your code as follows.
中文字幕
To not bother closing it explicitly, to instead use a keyword called with
to instead put the variable name back there and indent everything underneath.
中文字幕
Doesn't matter for our purposes which one you do.
The first one was correct.
中文字幕
The second one is correct.
This is just more conventional, if only because it handles
中文字幕
the closing of the file for you.
So if you see this online, that's all that's happening there.
中文字幕
But it's just like in C doing fopen and fclose, or in this case open and close
like I had a moment ago.
中文字幕
Any questions, then?
How would you handle duplicates?
中文字幕
How would I duplicates?
good question.
中文字幕
So haven't handled duplicates here at all, and David from Matthews
could register again and again.
中文字幕
But logically what might I do?
Well, it probably belongs here in my register route.
中文字幕
I probably want to do more error checking than just these two lines.
Because what I probably want to do to see if David from Matthews
中文字幕
is already registered is open the CSV file,
iterate over its lines looking for David and for Matthews on the same line
中文字幕
and then show a failure to the user if he or she is
trying to register for a second time.
中文字幕
I've not made it easy with this code, and frankly that's
going to be so much easier next week with SQL.
中文字幕
SQL, this other language for databases, will
make it easy to search data that has already been saved.
中文字幕
CSV files do not make this easy.
It's doable, but you have to write more lines of code.
中文字幕
So more on that to come.
Other questions?
中文字幕
All right, so let's skip ahead to one final example,
froshim6, which we'll do something a little more for us here.
中文字幕
So if I go ahead into froshim6, notice that if I
do Flask run, and go back to the website here, and reload the screen,
中文字幕
and I go ahead and give you my name, but no, I'm not going to give you my dorm,
we have this feature.
中文字幕
It's ugly again, but where did we see this kind of functionality
when the user does not cooperate?
中文字幕
Or how did I implement this, apparently?
JavaScript?
中文字幕
Yeah, JavaScript.
So it turns out that with Python, you can obviously
中文字幕
validate the user's input on the server by just checking what's
in request.args or request.form and then yell at the user success or failure
中文字幕
accordingly.
But you can also use JavaScript-- and honestly, we did this two weeks ago,
中文字幕
so we just seem to be solving the same problems again.
So how do you think about this?
中文字幕
Should I be checking for the user's name and dorm in JavaScript?
Should I be checking for the user's name and dorm on the server?
中文字幕
I mean, mixed messages now.
Whatever's fastest.
中文字幕
Whatever fastest.
That's a pretty good heuristic to use, what's fastest.
中文字幕
And we can make it prettier by using Bootstrap or some library
to give you like a colorful box, or red error text or something like that.
中文字幕
So which probably is faster, Python or JavaScript?
JavaScript.
中文字幕
Why, is JavaScript just a better, faster language?
You're not creating it
中文字幕
Say again?
You're not creating it on a new server,
中文字幕
so it's all happening on the same--
That's why, yeah.
中文字幕
We don't have to get into the religious debate of which language
is better or faster, but where they're running is certainly important.
中文字幕
JavaScript is running, recall, by definition, in the browser.
It is sent as JavaScript code to the browser
中文字幕
which then executes it client side.
Python by definition today is doing everything server side.
中文字幕
And indeed, the browser doesn't even know
Python is involved, because all it gets is the HTML code that results.
中文字幕
So OK, that seems to be an argument for not
doing all of the new work we did today with if not name, if not dorm,
中文字幕
and all of that, and just use JavaScript.
But the problem is that if you get a little sloppy or a little clever
中文字幕
and only implement your error checking client side.
Because as you say, it's faster, and frankly once I make it prettier,
中文字幕
it's just going to be more interactive and more seamless.
The problem is you can't and should not trust users.
中文字幕
Suppose that I'm a malicious user and I just
want to inject some bogus data into your website, or I want to spam you,
中文字幕
or subscribe 1,000 freshmen who don't actually exist, or just
generally create problems for you.
中文字幕
Well, you might think, well, that's OK, I
have some defenses in place, and JavaScript code,
中文字幕
and this adversary is going to get very quick feedback, very pretty
feedback that they've not provided these various fields.
中文字幕
But honestly, you can't trust anything ever coming from the human.
If I open up Chrome's developer tools, and I
中文字幕
go to this down here to the dot dot dot menu, and I go to Settings,
and I go down here, there.
中文字幕
That's all it takes to disable all of your hard work.
He or she can just open up their browser--
中文字幕
Chrome or something else--
turn off JavaScript.
中文字幕
So now when I actually submit this form, there's
going to be no on-submit checking, no on-click handling.
中文字幕
All of that is disabled.
So if I go ahead and click Register, I at least
中文字幕
still, in this version of froshims, have server side checking, as well.
So this might be a little frustrating, but it's kind of the reality.
中文字幕
It is perfectly fine to use JavaScript code
and use client side code to give the user a better experience-- a.k.a.
中文字幕
UX, user experience.
But you can't cut corners and not implement
中文字幕
the same kind of logic server side because you
need to defend against this.
中文字幕
Otherwise bogus data is going to end up in your database,
things are going to go wrong.
中文字幕
Never, ever, ever trust the user.
Any questions?
中文字幕
Can you do the same via CSS?
Can you do the same with CSS?
中文字幕
Yes, can you JavaScript ??
Not with CSS alone.
中文字幕
You can use CSS to make the error messages far prettier, yes,
but not logically enough with CSS alone.
中文字幕
And in fact, just to give you a sense now how you can make things prettier
since I keep alluding to better design skills than the ones I'm showing here.
中文字幕
If we go to Bootstrap, this very popular, free, and open source
library for CSS, it actually has some interactive features, as well.
中文字幕
And if I go under components in the documentation and I scroll down
and I go to forms, you'll see, one, notice
中文字幕
that these forms are already way prettier than the ones
I've been making, right?
中文字幕
It's like black text, and gray text, and small text.
It just looks nicer and cleaner.
中文字幕
But it's relatively easy to do this.
And indeed, for the next problems that you'll
中文字幕
be welcome to copy and paste some of this sample code and HTML,
use Bootstrap CSS just to make your forms prettier.
中文字幕
But what it can really do if I go to the sub menu over here,
notice that there's this validation section in Bootstrap.
中文字幕
And other libraries have this, too.
And you'll want to read the actual documentation.
中文字幕
But if I just scroll down for a while, here's a sample form in Bootstrap.
It already looks a little prettier than anything I've made in just raw HTML.
中文字幕
But notice if I don't cooperate, you can do really cool validation of forms
with green and red text if the user does or doesn't
中文字幕
cooperate by using a mix of CSS, but with some JavaScript code.
And so what Bootstrap does for you is it actually
中文字幕
automates some of the process of that JavaScript code
that we saw two weeks ago and just used now.
中文字幕
But it doesn't just pop up a message for the user,
it actually gives them more immediate feedback.
中文字幕
And almost any popular web site you visit these days gives you
this more immediate proximal input.
中文字幕
Generally you don't see some simple error message popping up,
even though that's easier to do.
中文字幕
Any questions?
All right, so where did that logic come from?
中文字幕
So let me go into, for instance, my template
file now for the form in froshim6--
中文字幕
again, the last of these examples--
and you'll notice that I did this.
中文字幕
If I scroll through this file, you'll see the same HTML
as we've been using for some time.
中文字幕
But notice at the bottom of the page that I draw some inspiration
from two weeks back when we looked at HTML, and CSS, and JavaScript.
中文字幕
So just as a quick refresher, notice how this is working.
This line of code says in JavaScript check
中文字幕
the document using the query selector, which lets you select anything
in the web page looking for a form.
中文字幕
When that form is submitted, call the following anonymous function.
If the document query selector finds an input that does not have a value--
中文字幕
and I say not because of the exclamation point here--
then yell at the user with this, you must provide your name
中文字幕
and return false.
Else if the user did not provide a value for the select menu-- a.k.a. the dorm--
中文字幕
go ahead and alert them that they must provide the dorm,
otherwise return true.
中文字幕
And just to be clear and to recall from two weeks ago,
what am I returning false?
中文字幕
What does that effect have logically?
Yeah, say again?
中文字幕
What was that?
I heard a whisper here.
中文字幕
No?
Yeah, it prevents submission of the form.
中文字幕
The default behavior of a form is it wants to be submitted.
That's why they exist.
中文字幕
But if you return false in JavaScript, it
will short circuit that and prevent that default behavior,
中文字幕
thereby stopping the user from submitting the form at all.
So let's take one step back now, there's now so much going on in this one file
中文字幕
alone.
In this sixth and final example, notice that we
中文字幕
have application.py, which is the entry point, the so-called controller
of this web application.
中文字幕
It has a route which very simply for slash looks like this.
When the user gets slash, this template is simply returned.
中文字幕
What is in that index.html template?
Well, it contains a partial HTML file.
中文字幕
It contains this HTML.
But it does not contain the doctype, the HTML tag, head tag, the body tag,
中文字幕
the title tag, and all of that.
It only contains the stuff that should go inside of the body tag.
中文字幕
Because this file is using a bit of jinja,
which is the templating language that Flask uses.
中文字幕
You can just think of it as Flask, that's fine.
It uses some HTML here, but it also in the bottom of the file uses JavaScript.
中文字幕
And so just as before when we've looked at the source of the page, what
I'm going to see in the browser on this forms page is no jinja,
中文字幕
no Python, nothing related to Flask.
Just a fully formed HTML page that also now contains
中文字幕
some of that client side code.
And so I have this mixture now of several different language,
中文字幕
but each of which solves a very distinct problem.
Yeah?
中文字幕
So I think it was a week ago or two weeks ago when
we were working on JavaScript and CSS, you
中文字幕
were saying that it's preferable to split languages, not
mix them in the same document.
中文字幕
Right now we are mixing multiple languages.
Really good observation.
中文字幕
So a couple of weeks ago I really preached the separation of concerns,
and therefore separation of files.
中文字幕
And that's why we introduced a .css file,
we also briefly showed examples of a .js file.
中文字幕
The short answer is as your applications get more complex,
life starts to get messy.
中文字幕
And the team and I were actually talking about this
earlier as to how to present some of these examples,
中文字幕
because what you are seeing in my design decision here is a tension.
So that tension here is as follows.
中文字幕
It is not necessarily the best practice to just have your logical JavaScript
code comingled with your HTML.
中文字幕
It makes it harder to collaborate with someone else.
If one of you is really good at design and wants to work on the HTML and CSS,
中文字幕
the other person really wants to do the JavaScript code, kind of hard
to do that when they're both in the same file.
中文字幕
So we could factor this out.
I could change this line, just to be super clear, to be this.
中文字幕
Instead of putting my actual code in the file, I could do something like this.
The source of this shall be form.js, and that is just it.
中文字幕
And then I have a separate file maybe my colleague works in as follows.
But at some point the thoughts that go through my head
中文字幕
are, it's only like 10 lines of code and I just
have to create a second file now, and that second file
中文字幕
is going to be maybe in a different folder as my template.
And you know, it feels like this is just overengineering a solution
中文字幕
to the problem.
However, once it's 20 lines, 100 lines, now OK, now it's feeling messy.
中文字幕
Somewhere there's this inflection point.
And this is where reasonable people will disagree, and I might argue one way,
中文字幕
you might argue the other way.
And honestly, both of us are probably right.
中文字幕
And so this just speaks to the web's development over time.
And there's fancier frameworks now. and if we tie things earlier
中文字幕
into the question about CS50 beyond, an opportunity after this class that
looks more closely at web programming, there
中文字幕
are even fancier frameworks nowadays than Flask and than Bootstrap
that if tried to solve this problem.
中文字幕
React is one of the most popular ones developed by Facebook,
now open source and used by so many people
中文字幕
around the world that actually addresses this issue.
And it allows you to separate your HTML from your CSS
中文字幕
from your JavaScript in different parts of the file but still in the same file.
And that was their particular solution.
中文字幕
And View and Angular, there are so many different solutions to these problems.
And unfortunately, once we take the training wheels of CS50 off,
中文字幕
this is what's ahead of you.
The world is messy.
中文字幕
And the reason there are so many darn languages and frameworks is
because people like you have these instincts and think,
中文字幕
this could be done better.
And thus do we iterate and have new and new technologies.
中文字幕
But this is the kind of stuff-- and honestly, this
is the kind of silliness that changes over time.
中文字幕
The fundamentals of HTTP, and client side code,
and JavaScript code, those fundamentals are invariant
中文字幕
even as the implementation details change.
So the short answer is, could this be better?
中文字幕
Probably.
Could it be much better?
中文字幕
I don't know.
It really now becomes more of a debate among developers.
中文字幕
Good question.
All right, so let's now use some of these basic building
中文字幕
blocks to make a final set of examples that demonstrates
a feature with which most of us are pretty familiar reminiscent of what we
中文字幕
did two weeks ago with Google Search.
At the time we searched for cats.
中文字幕
Today we'll keep it a little simpler and a little less graphical
and just search for words.
中文字幕
Because you'll recall from our speller problem set,
you implemented a spell checker with 140,000 plus English words.
中文字幕
That's a pretty juicy dataset to search over,
and you're probably all familiar with autocomplete these days.
中文字幕
There's hardly a website these days that when you start typing it
doesn't try to finish your thought for you.
中文字幕
Google, Facebook, any a number of other sites.
So autocomplete, how does that work?
中文字幕
Well, let me propose the following mental model.
If you do have some data set like a big list of words,
中文字幕
or a big list of Facebook friends, or a big list of whatever,
you might store that server side because it's a lot, a lot of data.
中文字幕
And in fact, next week you might store in a big database.
But for today we'll just store it in a file
中文字幕
like we did for the speller piece set.
But if you want to create an interactive experience
中文字幕
for the human, what language are you're probably
going to want to use so that he or she gets immediate feedback?
中文字幕
Probably JavaScript, right?
That's the whole principle.
中文字幕
Client side code is just going to execute faster because there's
no internet between you and the code.
中文字幕
But with Python, you have access to files.
And yet with JavaScript code you have closer access to the user,
中文字幕
so there's these tensions.
So how could we go about building a site that lets a human via form search
中文字幕
across that file for words?
Well, let's start as follows.
中文字幕
So in word 0 we have the following.
Large, which is just a text file borrowed from the speller problem set,
中文字幕
140,000 words, one poor line therein.
I'm not even going to double click and open it
中文字幕
because it's so darn big it'll take a few seconds to open.
In application.py we have probably the entry point to this application,
中文字幕
and in templates we have just three templates this time.
So just when you're reading someone else's code for the first time,
中文字幕
where should our entry point be?
Where should we start looking to understand what's going on?
中文字幕
Maybe application.py.
Or honestly, you know what?
中文字幕
If you want to see what something does, run it.
No harm in doing that.
中文字幕
So lets run Flask run.
Make this a little bit bigger.
中文字幕
Let me open up the URL here, open, and I see a very simple form
asking me for a query.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and search for a and click Search.
And after a moment, OK.
中文字幕
This is a lot of words, but apparently these
are all the English words that our dictionary knows
中文字幕
about that start with the letter a.
And if I go all the way to the bottom, you'll
中文字幕
see it stops with az whatever with no B words, in fact.
Well, let's make sure this actually works and isn't just a trick.
中文字幕
Let's search for b words.
OK, so that seems to work, as well.
中文字幕
And notice I borrowed some inspiration from Google.
Notice that the route I'm using is called slash search like two weeks ago.
中文字幕
Does take a cue parameter for query, and b is whatever the human typed in.
So if I want to search for z the words, enter,
中文字幕
I should hopefully get back now z words.
So now unlike two weeks ago, we can implement both the front end
中文字幕
and the back end for a search engine.
But our search engine's searching now just for words.
中文字幕
So let's look at application.py as proposed, which is the entry point,
and let's see how I'm doing this.
中文字幕
So this is some code that I borrowed a little bit from last week
when we quickly implemented the spell checker
中文字幕
in like 12 or 20 lines of Python code.
I'm declaring a global variable called words,
中文字幕
and I capitalized it just to be reminiscent of last time
and the problem set.
中文字幕
I'm using this syntax which I alluded to earlier
is just more conventional or Pythonic.
中文字幕
Open the large file in Read mode and call the variable file.
Then here is a for loop via which you can iterate over
中文字幕
every line in the file, reading one at a time.
But recall, what does every line in this file end with?
中文字幕
Like a backslash n, and we don't really want those as part of the words.
That's not part of the English word.
中文字幕
So R strip, right strip removes any whitespace from the end of the string.
And that's why I needed to add that extra line.
中文字幕
So I'm just cleaning up the file or massaging the data
as you might do with any sort of data based application.
中文字幕
So then I just seem to have this route that renders the template.
If I look in index.html, let's follow the bread crumbs.
中文字幕
Go into index.html.
OK, not that much going on here.
中文字幕
Looks like an HTML form, the action of which is slash search,
just like Google's.
中文字幕
The method of which is is get just like Google's.
There's nothing really private about the words I'm searching for here,
中文字幕
so I don't care.
There's some fancier features here.
中文字幕
Notice placeholder is the grayed out text the human sees.
Auto focus.
中文字幕
What does this do again?
This is just a UI feature, better user experience.
中文字幕
Puts the like, right in the text box.
Yeah, it puts the cursor right in the text box.
中文字幕
To focus on something in a web page means make it what's
interacting with the user right now.
中文字幕
And Mac OS, for instance, highlights it in blue.
So when you first load the page, the cursoe's
中文字幕
blinking in the choice of text boxes that you care about most.
Autocomplete off just disables the browser's version of autocomplete.
中文字幕
So I don't see past searches, just because the whole point here
is to implement this ourselves ultimately,
中文字幕
and then I have my search button.
This is just jinja stuff from Flask so that I have a layout file.
中文字幕
Lets follow that breadcrumb.
Lay out.html, nothing really that interesting going on there.
中文字幕
If you've ever wondered why we have these in a lot of our demos,
this cryptic looking line here just makes web sites look better
中文字幕
on mobile devices.
Typically by default if you pull up your phone and look at a website,
中文字幕
if it doesn't have that kind of line, like
the text is going to be super tiny unless you pinch and zoom.
中文字幕
By using this line and variations thereof,
it will increase the default font size a bit
中文字幕
to make it a little more tolerable on small screen.
So it's an easy win for users experience.
中文字幕
OK, I seem to have exhausted all the interesting stuff in these templates.
Let's look at another and final route.
中文字幕
Here's my search route, and this is pretty Pythonic.
This is a mouthful, and will re-implement it
中文字幕
in a different way in just a moment.
So I have a search route that listens for get requests on slash search.
中文字幕
Then this crazy looking line is about as Pythonic as code gets.
And I'll explain what this is doing and why
中文字幕
it's conventional as opposed to straightforward at first glance.
And then I render the template, passing in these words.
中文字幕
So this one liner on line 17 actually has the effect
of searching 140,000 words for whatever words
中文字幕
start with what the user typed in.
See, this would be a pain in the neck to do.
中文字幕
In Python you can do it with literally one line.
A long line, but one line nonetheless.
中文字幕
Let me make this more clear.
If I were to search for words in this big file,
中文字幕
I might do something like this.
Words is an empty list.
中文字幕
So this lower case words is all of the words that match,
that I want to send back to the user.
中文字幕
So by default I have no idea what to send back.
But I do know I can do this.
中文字幕
For word in Words--
which is the capitalized variable, the constant up at the top
中文字幕
that has the whole-- or not even constant,
but the global variable that has all of the words from the file, here
中文字幕
is a for loop over those.
I can now say something like this.
中文字幕
If the current word starts with whatever the user typed in-- well,
what's the user typing in?
中文字幕
Well, q equals request.args.get quote-unquote q,
gives me the user's name, dorm, or in this case Q value for query.
中文字幕
So if the word that we're currently iterating over starts with q,
I can go ahead and append to my-- whoops, append to this list that word.
中文字幕
Would you say you're comfortable with these lines here?
To recap, give me an empty list in which to store the search results,
中文字幕
iterate over all possible 140,000 plus words, get--
and actually, this was stupid.
中文字幕
I should just put this up here, because I only need to check for that once.
So store the user's input in a variable called q.
中文字幕
For each word among the 140,000, check if it starts with the user's input--
a, b, z, whatever.
中文字幕
And if so, append it to there.
So let's temporarily get rid of this and just render the template.
中文字幕
So notice this gets the job done, but this is very C-like logic.
It's not wrong, it's perfectly correct.
中文字幕
But Python is a language that's meant to be
a little more human readable and a little more elegant,
中文字幕
if a little more non-obvious.
So this one line does the exact same thing
中文字幕
using a feature called a list comprehension, which
is ironic if you don't quite comprehend how it's working.
中文字幕
But here's the variable I want to create called Words.
These square brackets here say give me a list.
中文字幕
What do you want to put in that list?
I want to put a word in this list.
中文字幕
Which word do you want to put in this list?
The result of inducing this loop and then only putting in this list
中文字幕
a word if it starts with what the human typed in.
So it takes some getting used to, but this is just
中文字幕
a one liner way, a very Pythonic way of expressing those several lines of very
procedural code into a simple one line.
中文字幕
Is it better?
Not if you can't read it.
中文字幕
But once you get more comfortable with Python,
yes, it's better because it's less code.
中文字幕
Yeah?
You said Python uses notation to tell where conditions are.
中文字幕
How is ?
Good question.
中文字幕
In this case of a list comprehension, you can only
have one line or one condition.
中文字幕
You can't have multiple lines therein, so I cannot start hitting Enter
and indenting here.
中文字幕
It's just not allowed.
So you would only use this-- and I'm frankly really pushing the limits.
中文字幕
You should only really use this syntax when it fits on your screen
or fits on a reasonable person's screen.
中文字幕
After that you should probably do something a little more expressive.
Other questions?
中文字幕
But this is very common to see online.
So any tutorials, if you ever see this kind of one liner,
中文字幕
just try to think about it from that approach what it is actually doing.
OK, so propose from a user experience perspective
中文字幕
how could this program be better?
Because this is just our first version.
中文字幕
So what could be better for the user than this?
What could be better?
中文字幕
Yeah?
Just going back, can you explain words in caps?
中文字幕
Oh, sure.
Words in caps is this global variable I defined up here that stores all 140,000
中文字幕
plus words.
That's the really big file called large, the text file.
中文字幕
Down here I just need a local variable.
And if it's more clear, I could call it results and then just
中文字幕
say results equals results.
That is the subset of words that start with a, or b,
中文字幕
or whatever the human typed in.
That's all.
中文字幕
Good question.
Yeah?
中文字幕
Why do we change the last time-- why
did you have to change args to form?
中文字幕
Why did I have to change my args to--
Forms?
中文字幕
So earlier today when I didn't understand what was going on,
you should use request.args for get requests.
中文字幕
You should use request.form for post requests.
But it's still .get after?
中文字幕
It's always .get, yes.
But you change what you're getting things from.
中文字幕
In an ideal world, it would have been something-- oh, I see what you mean.
Get in this sense is the verb.
中文字幕
We humans mean go get something.
Args in this sense, if they had done get--
中文字幕
I'm making this up, but this is probably why they did this.
Because get from get seems weird, whereas get from post is less weird.
中文字幕
But it's just they called it args and form instead.
OK, so let's actually improve this, but how?
中文字幕
What could be better for the user?
Yeah?
中文字幕
They could search a word, not just the first letter.
OK, maybe searching a whole word
中文字幕
would be good, not just the first letter.
What else could we do?
中文字幕
We can create an index list of letters and words?
OK, we could create an index list.
中文字幕
So maybe using a hash or some form of inspiration from our problem
set with Speller and actually use a more sophisticated data structure
中文字幕
to get these answers more quickly.
And let me propose, too, the goal here is to actually implement autocomplete,
中文字幕
and this was not auto complete.
This was like old school search.
中文字幕
Type in a query, hit Enter, get a page of results.
What if we want to do something more immediate?
中文字幕
So let me actually propose this.
Before looking at the code, let me go into words 1.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and run Flask in that directory.
Let me go ahead and reload the form here,
中文字幕
and now notice no Submit button because there's not going
to be any actual submissions here.
中文字幕
But I'm going to go ahead and hit the letter A, and ooh, that's kind of cool.
Let me delete that, goes away.
中文字幕
B, there's all the B words.
Let me go B-A words, B-A-B words, B-A-B-A words.
中文字幕
This is how autocomplete works.
So it seems to be responding immediately to my input, so something's happening.
中文字幕
But I'm not actually submitting the form.
So I'm kind of using it now, it seems client side JavaScript
中文字幕
to maybe talk to the server?
Let's infer.
中文字幕
So here, too, this should be your instinct.
Whenever you're trying to understand how someone's website works,
中文字幕
if you want to learn from it or mimic certain fundamental functionality,
go ahead and inspect the page.
中文字幕
And you don't probably care too much about the HTML yet.
Where is this data coming from?
中文字幕
Let me click on the Network tab, which we looked at a couple of weeks ago.
Let me go ahead and restart this and let me clear this and start
中文字幕
from the beginning of the story.
Let's see what happens when I type the letter A. Interesting.
中文字幕
There is a web request.
So if I zoom in down here, notice that my browser actually searched
中文字幕
for Q equals A, the human's input.
Let me go ahead and-- it keeps searching because I'm
中文字幕
using keyboard shortcuts here.
But let me go ahead and click this row.
中文字幕
Notice what happened.
I made a request to slash search question mark q equals a via get.
中文字幕
Let's see what the response was.
The response here, if I view the source--
中文字幕
or rather, if I read the response--
notice what came back.
中文字幕
It looks like my server returned to me a fragment of HTML containing hundreds,
maybe thousands of words starting with A. But notice there's no UL tag,
中文字幕
there's no head tag, no title, no body, it's just a partial HTML fragment.
But that's interesting, because I know with Python I can do exactly that.
中文字幕
I can generate anything I want on the server,
and then maybe the browser can just plug in those changed the results.
中文字幕
So let me go ahead and look at the code for this page.
If I go now to the browser's source code, the view page source,
中文字幕
you'll see a few new lines.
So to do this easily, I'm actually using another library.
中文字幕
This one is called jQuery.
This was for many years super, super popular.
中文字幕
It's kind of starting to fall out of vogue,
but it's still so powerful and so useful.
中文字幕
And it's used by Bootstrap, the other CSS library we've talked about,
so it's perfectly reasonable to use it here.
中文字幕
Notice how I'm including it with the script tag,
and it's hosted on a third party website so
中文字幕
that I don't have to save a copy of it myself on my own IDE.
Then let's look at the code I actually wrote.
中文字幕
So notice that atop this file is not even a full fledged form,
it is just the HTML input.
中文字幕
Because I don't need a full form.
I don't need an action, I don't need a method,
中文字幕
because I'm not submitting it anywhere with the human's cooperation.
I'm going to use my own code.
中文字幕
So in my script tag here, my JavaScript code, notice what I'm doing.
This is some code from like two weeks ago.
中文字幕
I'm going to search the tree that represents this web page.
And indeed, it is meant to be a tree.
中文字幕
Recall from that time when we looked at an HTML page,
there is in memory, thanks to the browser, something treelike--
中文字幕
a DOM, document object model-- that represents your page.
Using JavaScript, can we change that page after the fact?
中文字幕
So what am I going to do?
I'm going to tell the browser whenever this input hears an event called on key
中文字幕
up-- so whenever the field has focus-- it's blue in Mac OS--
and the human hits the key and then let's go,
中文字幕
and the key goes up, go ahead and call the following anonymous function.
What do you want that to do?
中文字幕
Now, this code is a little cryptic, but let
me walk us through it because it's only three lines.
中文字幕
This code here is using a special feature--
dollar sign-- that comes from this library called jQuery.
中文字幕
More on that in a moment.
That library, somewhat confusingly named, has a function called get,
中文字幕
which has nothing to do with Python or the one we just talked about.
But this has to do with an HTTP get.
中文字幕
With this line of code, you can tell a browser,
even after a web page has been loaded, go get me this other URL, please.
中文字幕
So what URL do you want to get?
Go ahead and get me from the same server slash search q equals,
中文字幕
and then what does plus mean in JavaScript if you recall?
Concatenation.
中文字幕
So it means just append one string to the other.
So this is like saying, go ahead and get me
中文字幕
the URL that ends with slash search, question mark, Q equals A, or Q equals
B, or Q equals Z. Whatever the human typed and just gets
中文字幕
slapped onto the end.
And then that's where we're getting it from.
中文字幕
Input.value is the user's input, the value thereof.
And then the last line-- and this is perhaps the fanciest--
中文字幕
notice that I have an anonymous function.
In this library called jQuery, there is this function
中文字幕
called get that gets a URL.
When the server responds to your request with a virtual envelope of its own,
中文字幕
this anonymous function gets called and the response envelope
gets handed to you, so to speak, as a data argument, as a data variable.
中文字幕
Then what you can you do?
Document.queryselector UL.
中文字幕
What is UL?
It's an unordered list that by default on this page has nothing in it.
中文字幕
But recall that what the server is sending back is a bunch of LI tags.
That's great, because I want to put those LI tags right in between here.
中文字幕
So how do I do that?
I go into the so-called inner HTML of the UL tag,
中文字幕
and you might not have seen this before.
But you can change the contents of an existing tag inside of it
中文字幕
by using inner HTML and just plop the data in there.
And so what's happening is this.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and open up Chrome's inspector.
Reload the page so it's empty.
中文字幕
Let me open up Chrome's inspector.
Go to elements, as is the default. And notice on this page,
中文字幕
notice that UL tag is opened and closed with nothing inside of it.
The moment, though, I search for something, watch what happens.
中文字幕
If I search for a, all of a sudden--
ooh, it blinked, it's a little small.
中文字幕
Now there's a little triangle there.
What's inside of it?
中文字幕
All of those LI tags that came from the server.
So with JavaScript, we have this amazing power now
中文字幕
to change what's inside of a web page by just asking the server for more data.
So if you've ever used Facebook, or you've
中文字幕
used Google Chat, or any websites that's dynamically changing every second,
every minute and each time you get a message, you can literally,
中文字幕
if you get a little nosy, open up Chrome's inspector and watch the DOM,
watch this elements tab.
中文字幕
And you'll see new stuff popping up every time
you get a message, or a chat, or any other such notification on the screen.
中文字幕
Now as an aside, this is a little sloppy to be returning HTML,
but let's see how it's done.
中文字幕
Let me go into application.py for words one, which is this example here.
And in application.py, notice what I'm doing is this.
中文字幕
Rather than return a whole page of results,
I'm returning a template called search.html.
中文字幕
All of the rest of this code is identical to before.
If I go into my templates and go into search.html, look how terribly simple
中文字幕
the code is on the server.
If all you want to do is spit out a bunch of list items,
中文字幕
this is all you need.
There's no template.
中文字幕
Like there's no extends layout because you're not returning a whole web page,
you're returning a tiny, tiny, tiny fragment of HTML.
中文字幕
But this is arguably a little sloppy, because there's
a lot of redundancy in what's coming back.
中文字幕
If I look at this tag that's coming back from the server,
what is obviously redundant about all of this information that's coming back?
中文字幕
And if I look at the Network tab, you really see it under response.
What's redundant?
中文字幕
You're doing a bunch of calls to the same address and to the same--
This was just because I hit some, like, zoom in and zoom out,
中文字幕
so it pretended to make multiple requests.
So red herring there.
中文字幕
Focus only on this part here.
What's redundant about all of the data coming back?
中文字幕
It's just keeps saying list item, word, close list item.
List item, word, clothes list item.
中文字幕
I mean come on, just use a more efficient syntax.
Just separate things with commas or something lighter weight.
中文字幕
This is sending way many bytes.
I mean, look.
中文字幕
There's thousands of bytes.
This is kilobytes by definition of information
中文字幕
that we're sending just to send open bracket,
LI close bracket again and again.
中文字幕
This is not very efficient.
And so the world actually has adopted a different approach,
中文字幕
and I'm going to show this in words 2 that actually returns something called
JavaScript Object Notation, which is a more succinct representation of this
中文字幕
as follows.
Let me go into words 2, run Flask in there.
中文字幕
Search for the same kind of thing and then watch
what happens over the network panel this time.
中文字幕
When I search for A, immediately get back the same visual result.
But if I look at this search query, now look what comes back.
中文字幕
I claim that this is a much more compact representation of the same information.
It's a little annoying that there's double quotes,
中文字幕
because those are a little redundant.
But at least double quotes are a lot more efficient
中文字幕
than open bracket, LI, closed bracket, and then the opposite at the end.
So this is what's called JavaScript Object Notation.
中文字幕
And as this square bracket here and thousands
of words later the square bracket on the end implies,
中文字幕
this is a JavaScript array that's being sent back from the server.
So the only thing that's changed here is as follows.
中文字幕
In words 2, this example, notice that I don't even
need to return a template anymore.
中文字幕
This code is the same as the past two examples.
This is how I'm searching 140,000 words quickly.
中文字幕
But if I include now a fancier function from Flask called jsonify--
which is not really a word.
中文字幕
But jsonify, that takes any data structure
you have data in like this list of words, the matches,
中文字幕
and it turns it into that text based representation with quotes and commas.
And you don't even have to write a template yourself.
中文字幕
And indeed, I got rid of search.html.
The only thing you have to do to give yourself access to this feature
中文字幕
is import not just render template, and request,
and Flask, but jsonify, as well, from the Flask library.
中文字幕
Which is just one more feature.
Any questions on that before we bring it all together with one final example?
中文字幕
Yeah?
Can double quotes break that into ??
中文字幕
Can double quotes break that?
Good question, great instincts.
中文字幕
No because the author of jsonify was smart about this.
And if that author notices a quote like an apostrophe, or like something
中文字幕
in your own name that has a quote, it will escape it in some way,
usually with a backslash.
中文字幕
Good instincts.
But that's why you probably wouldn't want to write this code yourself
中文字幕
because then you have to think of all of those corner cases as opposed
to focusing on the parts you care about.
中文字幕
All right, so there's one final example.
And it's perhaps to come full circle here, do we even need the server?
中文字幕
These 140,000 words right now are in a file called large.
My web application loads that file into memory and then searches it.
中文字幕
But who else could search over a big list of files?
Where else could we put this logic?
中文字幕
The browser, right?
Browser gives you JavaScript, JavaScript's a language,
中文字幕
languages can search things.
So let me try this instead.
中文字幕
In our words 3 example here, notice that I've got one new file.
In advance, you know, I took my big text file that just had one word per line
中文字幕
and I put it into a standard format just because it
makes my life a little easier.
中文字幕
And I called it large.json.
And in there, actually, where if I open up this folder, you'll see large.js,
中文字幕
which is a second file, this time a JavaScript file,
in which I've just declared a JavaScript array of all 140,000 words
中文字幕
for better or for worse.
I just put them into a slightly different format
中文字幕
with commas, and quotes, and square brackets,
and I gave this whole thing a variable name at the very top of the file.
中文字幕
Now, why is this useful?
Well, if I go into index.html, notice that there
中文字幕
is no more application.py or templates for this example whatsoever.
We've gotten rid of Python entirely, I don't
中文字幕
know if it's for the better or worse, but we'll now see.
So in this file, notice we have an input tag as before,
中文字幕
a placeholder for all of the ULs, but we're also
now including this large.js file.
中文字幕
Thereby telling the browser please download all 140,000 words
and then search them locally.
中文字幕
How am I going to search it locally?
I've essentially converted the language I wrote in Python a bit
中文字幕
ago into JavaScript as follows.
Here says the browser go get me the input that the user can type into.
中文字幕
This tells the browser, go ahead and listen for key up.
Whenever that happens, please call this function
中文字幕
which has no name, because I want you to just call it immediately,
I don't need its name.
中文字幕
This function is defined by these several lines.
These several lines have to do a bit more work than before.
中文字幕
Because before the server was doing all the hard work
sending back all of the data, and we just jammed it into the web page.
中文字幕
But here I'm going to build up a list a little more manually.
So I'm going to let a variable called html
中文字幕
equals quote unquote, because I want to build up the unordered list myself.
Then if the human, indeed, types something in--
中文字幕
so if their input is non null, so if they type at least one character,
do the following.
中文字幕
This is weird in JavaScript, but when you
iterate over an array in JavaScript, you use the preposition of not in.
中文字幕
So for word of words, go ahead and do the following.
If the current word starts with-- notice the capitalized w-- also
中文字幕
different from Python, but same idea, just different spelling--
if the word I'm iterating over starts with whatever the human inputted,
中文字幕
we found a match.
Go ahead and append to this HTML variable,
中文字幕
open bracket LI closed bracket, concatenate the word to it,
and then close bracket, as well.
中文字幕
So I'm constructing a variable in the browser's memory
containing HTML that I want to jam into the DOM ultimately.
中文字幕
How do I do that.
Well, at the very last line I say to the document, select the UL tag,
中文字幕
go inside of its HTML, and change whatever
is there to this string of HTML, which is presumably 0 or more LI tags
中文字幕
now based on those search results.
So now let me go back to words 1--
中文字幕
rather, let me go back to this example here.
Let me go ahead and serve this up.
中文字幕
It's not Flask anymore, so I have to use our server from two weeks ago,
HTTP server, to serve up HTML.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and reload the screen here, open up index.html, and now
notice we're good to go.
中文字幕
What do you want to search for?
A, B, C. And let's open up the Network tab.
中文字幕
Inspect, Network.
Let's see what happens every time I search.
中文字幕
Z, Y, Q, A. Why is there no network traffic now?
There's no network traffic.
中文字幕
OK, but that's what I said.
But why is there no network traffic?
中文字幕
It's not sending any routes, it's not talking to a backend server.
Why?
中文字幕
Because all the data I might need is already local.
So mixed messages here, too.
中文字幕
Which is better, which is right?
What's the takeaway?
中文字幕
How do you think about this?
Because now, whereas a lot of our programs early on in the semester
中文字幕
were relatively small even though they didn't feel that way at the time,
now we have even more design possibilities.
中文字幕
And the answers are increasingly non-obvious,
and this is why you as programmers will just
中文字幕
get more comfortable with conventions, you'll maybe
practice what you've seen preached first,
中文字幕
then you'll decide as you might be already saying,
I don't like that, I'm going to do this some other way.
中文字幕
So how do you think about which of these several words examples is best?
Version 0 was let the server do all the work
中文字幕
and just send back a full new page of results like Google in 1999 did.
Then version 1, we added a bit of JavaScript
中文字幕
that used jQuery the library to talk to the server using
a technique called Ajax--
中文字幕
asynchronous JavaScript and XML--
but that just means go get me more data and we returned LI elements.
中文字幕
Then we decided that's a little sloppy, don't
seem to send me all these useless tags, just
中文字幕
send a comma separated list of words.
That was version 2.
中文字幕
And then this last version gets rid of all of that
and just sends all the words to the browser
中文字幕
and lets it deal with it entirely.
Who likes which best, 0, 1, 2, or 3?
中文字幕
What do you think?
So if you aren't supposed to trust the user in case
中文字幕
they turn off the JavaScript, then their decision of the functionality
of the website works.
中文字幕
That's a good trade-off.
So if the user turns off JavaScript, 3--
中文字幕
OK, it won't offend anyone--
3 2, and 1 won't work anymore because JavaScript's disabled.
中文字幕
Now, do you care about that?
Maybe not.
中文字幕
It's a small number of users on the internet who
are so concerned with this they just turn off JavaScript altogether,
中文字幕
and the reality is so many websites just break these days without JavaScript.
That might be a reasonable cost of doing business.
中文字幕
Other thoughts?
Yeah?
中文字幕
Is the last version the fastest?
I don't know, how could we assess that?
中文字幕
Yeah, I mean, we can literally measure it.
And honestly, built into Chrome in other tabs that I've not even clicked on
中文字幕
are a lot of performance tools where you can actually
monitor how long everything's taking.
中文字幕
This is called benchmarking more generally,
and this is what you did essentially in the speller problems
中文字幕
that even though we wrote the code that timed everything
and measured everything, to answer that question,
中文字幕
you could just try timing every one of the examples
and then decide for yourself which is best, sure.
中文字幕
Yeah?
The last thing I have with problematic issue
中文字幕
is like my phone's old, and it doesn't have a lot of memory,
and I may not have the fastest plan on Earth.
中文字幕
So you might be charging me more data, you might be slowing my phone down.
Very reasonable concern.
中文字幕
Let me go into our dictionary file here and list the size of this.
That large.js file is 2.2 megabytes, which on mobile devices,
中文字幕
especially in places where your signal is slow, or your bytes are expensive,
or you only have intermittent access, I mean,
中文字幕
that's kind of obnoxious to send two megabytes to the user
if you can avoid it, especially when you can send only the subset of results,
中文字幕
a few kilobytes maybe, of matches instead.
So a very reasonable concern.
中文字幕
Cost, user experience, performance.
Other thoughts?
中文字幕
Which is better for people on university and corporate campuses who tend
to have really good internet access?
中文字幕
Say again?
3, OK.
中文字幕
But what if it's not 140,000 words, but it's
like a billion pictures of cats that Google indexes?
中文字幕
Or hundreds or thousands of friends and all of their profile data?
Like at some point there's this inflection point
中文字幕
where too much data, right?
It's not reasonable, it's too much.
中文字幕
You don't want to just get a copy of your corporate database
to every one of your users just for them to search more locally.
中文字幕
So again, these are the non-obvious questions.
And one of the goals of, frankly, the final project
中文字幕
if you do something web based, or mobile based, or C based, or anything,
is all of these questions now boil down to you.
中文字幕
Like we have no well-defined answers in mind
as to what your final project should do and how it should do it best.
中文字幕
But in the weeks ahead, you'll be pre-proposing some project ideas,
proposing an actual project idea, and then designing and implementing this.
中文字幕
And you, too, will probably feel this tension
where the answer is not always obvious, your teaching fellow might not even
中文字幕
know how to answer your question, because he or she will
have thoughts of their own.
中文字幕
But it's ultimately up to you.
And we're now at the point of a level of coding maturity
中文字幕
where we're taking the training wheels off and more of the decisions
are now left to you.
中文字幕
Let's end here.
Stick around for one on one questions, and we'll
中文字幕
see you next week for databases.